<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
	<element
		name="Choke Hold"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Judo-2, Wrestling-3, or appropriate weapon skill-3."
		prereq="Judo, Wrestling, or appropriate weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite."
		desc="This close-combat attack involves locking the target’s neck and applying pressure. It requires two hands. Roll against Choke Hold to hit. If you come from in front of your victim, you’re at -1.

Your victim may try any legal defense. If they fail, you apply the hold, which counts as a grapple. If you struck from behind, they can only defend if they knew you were coming (see GURPS Basic Set, p. 391). Otherwise, all they can do is attempt to tuck their chin to counter your hold. This is a parry at -2 with a grappling skill. They can’t retreat. If they succeed, you grapple them but get no hold; critical success means they completely duck your attack.

On your foe’s next turn and on subsequent turns, they may try to break free. You’re at +5 in the Quick Contest for using two hands. You control only their neck and head, not their arms and legs. They can attack you at the usual -4 for being grappled. If you came from behind, they may only try the strikes detailed under Pain and Breaking Free (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 119) or attempt to grapple your arm, which allows the usual follow-up techniques on later turns.

On your next turn – and on each turn thereafter, until your prey breaks free – you may apply pressure to your victim’s carotid arteries to subdue them or to their trachea to choke them. This counts as an attack. Roll the Quick Contest described in Choke or Strangle (see GURPS Basic Set, p. 370). Your hold gives you +3 ST. A carotid ('blood') choke inflicts fatigue damage. A tracheal ('air') choke delivers crushing damage.

You can apply this hold using a weapon. Default and prerequisite skills become a weapon skill. The lever gives a further ST bonus to restrain or injure your victim: +1 if reach C, +2 if longer. You can choke with the flat or the edge of a sword; if using the edge, you may only choke for cutting damage. You must grasp a sword with one hand on the handle, one on the blade. Make a DX roll when you roll to inflict injury. Failure does thrust cutting damage to your off hand (DR protects normally)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Arm Lock"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Prerequisite skill."
		prereq="Judo, Wrestling, or appropriate Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		desc="An arm lock is an attempt to restrain or cripple an opponent by twisting their arm. It normally uses Judo or Wrestling skill. This technique lets you improve effective skill for this purpose only.

To use Arm Lock, you must have two hands free and make a successful barehanded parry with Judo or Wrestling against your opponent’s melee attack. On your first turn following the parry, you may attempt to capture your attacker’s arm if they’re still within one yard. This is an attack: step into close combat and roll against Arm Lock to hit. Your foe may use any active defense – they can parry your hand with a weapon! If their defense fails, you trap their arm.

Your foe may attempt to break free (GURPS Basic Set, p. 371) on their next turn, but you’re at +4 in the Quick Contest. If they lose, they have a cumulative -1 on future attempts to break free.

On your next turn – and each turn thereafter, until your foe breaks free – you may try to damage the trapped arm. Roll a Quick Contest: the higher of your ST (including your Wrestling bonus) or Arm Lock vs. the higher of your victim’s ST or HT. If you win, you inflict crushing damage equal to your margin of victory. The target’s rigid DR protects normally. Flexible armor, including natural DR with the Flexible or Tough Skin limitation, has no effect.

If you cripple your victim’s arm, they drop anything in that hand. You can inflict no further damage on a crippled limb but you can continue to roll the Contest each turn. If you win, your target suffers shock and stunning just as if you had inflicted damage.

Rolls to inflict damage are completely passive and don’t count as attacks. You can simultaneously make close-combat attacks on your opponent, who defends at -4 in addition to any penalties due to injury caused by the lock itself. If you decide to throw them using the lock, this does count as an attack; see Throws from Locks (GURPS Basic Set, p. 118-119).

You can use this ability offensively as well. Instead of waiting to parry an attack, grapple your foe normally with Judo or Wrestling. If they fail to break free on their next turn, you may try Arm Lock on your next turn, just as if you had parried their attack.

You can also apply this lock with a weapon. Default and prerequisite skills become a weapon skill. To initiate the lock requires a weapon parry or an Armed Grapple (GURPS Basic Set, p. 67). A reach C weapon gets +1 in the Quick Contest to cause damage; anything longer gets +2. Edged weapons can inflict crushing or cutting damage, but you must make a DX roll when you roll to inflict injury. Failure does thrust cutting damage to your off hand (DR protects normally). Otherwise, use the rules above.

Arm Lock uses precision and skill to cripple a foe’s limb. For a brute-force technique, see Wrench (Limb) (GURPS Basic Set, p. 82)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Wrist Lock"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Prerequisite skill."
		prereq="Judo, Wrestling, or appropriate Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		desc="An wrist lock is an attempt to restrain or cripple an opponent by twisting their wrist. It normally uses Judo or Wrestling skill. This technique lets you improve effective skill for this purpose only.

To use Wrist Lock, you must have two hands free and make a successful barehanded parry with Judo or Wrestling against your opponent’s melee attack. On your first turn following the parry, you may attempt to capture your attacker’s wrist if they’re still within one yard. This is an attack: step into close combat and roll against Wrist Lock to hit. Your foe may use any active defense – they can parry your hand with a weapon! If their defense fails, you trap their wrist.

Your foe may attempt to break free (GURPS Basic Set, p. 371) on their next turn, but you’re at +4 in the Quick Contest. If they lose, they have a cumulative -1 on future attempts to break free.

On your next turn – and each turn thereafter, until your foe breaks free – you may try to damage the trapped wrist. Roll a Quick Contest: the higher of your ST (including your Wrestling bonus) or Wrist Lock vs. the higher of your victim’s ST or HT. If you win, you inflict crushing damage equal to your margin of victory. The target’s rigid DR protects normally. Flexible armor, including natural DR with the Flexible or Tough Skin limitation, has no effect.

If you cripple your victim’s wrist, they drop anything in that hand. You can inflict no further damage on a crippled limb but you can continue to roll the Contest each turn. If you win, your target suffers shock and stunning just as if you had inflicted damage.

Rolls to inflict damage are completely passive and don’t count as attacks. You can simultaneously make close-combat attacks on your opponent, who defends at -4 in addition to any penalties due to injury caused by the lock itself. If you decide to throw them using the lock, this does count as an attack; see Throws from Locks (GURPS Basic Set, p. 118-119).

You can use this ability offensively as well. Instead of waiting to parry an attack, grapple your foe normally with Judo or Wrestling. If they fail to break free on their next turn, you may try Wrist Lock on your next turn, just as if you had parried their attack.

You can also apply this lock with a weapon. Default and prerequisite skills become a weapon skill. To initiate the lock requires a weapon parry or an Armed Grapple (GURPS Basic Set, p. 67). A reach C weapon gets +1 in the Quick Contest to cause damage; anything longer gets +2. Edged weapons can inflict crushing or cutting damage, but you must make a DX roll when you roll to inflict injury. Failure does thrust cutting damage to your off hand (DR protects normally). Otherwise, use the rules above.

Wrist Lock uses precision and skill to cripple a foe’s limb. For a brute-force technique, see Wrench (Limb) (GURPS Basic Set, p. 82)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Back Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-4."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you kick against a foe to your rear without making a Wild Swing or changing facing – although your legs must be free in order to change stance. Back Kick defaults to Karate-4. To throw a 'back punch,' use Elbow Strike (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 71).

To use this technique, you must know that your adversary is behind you! Roll against Back Kick or Back Strike to hit, at an extra -1 if you target a specific hit location.

A Back Kick has standard reach and damage for a kick.

In all cases, you’re at -2 to all active defenses until your next turn. This is cumulative with the -2 to parry with a weapon in a Reversed Grip!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Back Strike"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-2."
		prereq="Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you kick or use a melee weapon against a foe to your rear without making a Wild Swing or changing facing – although your legs must be free in order to change stance. Back Strike defaults to Melee Weapon-2 and you must specialize; e.g., Back Strike (Staff). To throw a 'back punch,' use Elbow Strike (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 71).

To use this technique, you must know that your adversary is behind you! Roll against Back Kick or Back Strike to hit, at an extra -1 if you target a specific hit location.

A Back Strike can only reach an enemy within one yard, regardless of weapon length. Thrusting attacks do their usual damage; swinging attacks have -2 damage or -1 damage per die, whichever is worse. A Back Strike from a Reversed Grip (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 111-112) uses the reach and damage effects of that grip instead of those given here.

In all cases, you’re at -2 to all active defenses until your next turn. This is cumulative with the -2 to parry with a weapon in a Reversed Grip!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Disarming"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill."
		prereq="Any unarmed combat or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+5."
		desc="If you know this technique above default, you may use it instead of the underlying skill whenever you attack to disarm (see Striking at Weapons, GURPS Basic Set, p. 400). For instance, if you have Broadsword-14 and Disarming (Broadsword)-17, you disarm as if you had Broadsword-17. Penalties to hit the target weapon, including the -2 for using a non-fencing weapon, and modifiers in the Quick Contest (such as the +2 for Jitte/Sai and Whip weapons) apply normally."
	/>
	<element
		name="Dual-Weapon Attack"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-4."
		prereq="Any one-handed Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill. You may learn this technique for Guns (Pistol), even in a realistic campaign."
		desc="Normally, you are at -4 to attack with two weapons at once unless you make an All-Out Attack. This technique lets you 'buy off' that penalty. (Note that you must still learn Off-Hand Weapon Training, GURPS Basic Set, p. 232, to reduce the -4 for using the 'off' hand!) For detailed rules, see Dual-Weapon Attacks (GURPS Basic Set, p. 417).

You must learn Dual-Weapon Attack (DWA) separately for each skill. For instance, attacking with two axes requires two DWA (Axe/Mace) rolls, but attacking with an axe and a whip requires a DWA (Axe/Mace) roll and a DWA (Whip) roll.

DWA (Bow) lets you shoot two arrows at once from a bow, possibly at different targets! Heroic Archer halves the default penalty to -2. Readying a second arrow requires an extra Ready or use of Multiple Fast-Draw (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 103)"
	/>
	<element
		name="Elbow Strike"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Brawling-2 or Karate-2."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="You can jab an elbow into an enemy behind you in close combat. Roll against Elbow Strike to hit. There’s no modifier for not facing them, but add an extra -1 if you target a specific hit location. A hit inflicts thrust-1 crushing damage, plus skill bonuses. Treat an elbow to someone in front of you as a punch.

Elbows are short-ranged and hard to hurt. You may not select All-Out Attack (Long) (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 97-98). Hurting Yourself (GURPS Basic Set, p. 379) applies, but damage is 1/10 of what you roll – not 1/5 – and both it and injury from enemy parries affects the arm, not the hand."
	/>
	<element
		name="Feint"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill."
		prereq="Any unarmed combat or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		desc="If you know this technique above default, you may use it instead of the underlying skill whenever you feint (see Feint, GURPS Basic Set, p. 365). For instance, if you have Broadsword-14 and Feint (Broadsword)-16, you feint as if you had Broadsword-16.

Feints aren’t always phony attacks. They include breaks in rhythm, false steps, head fakes, and other ploys to misdirect the foe. This technique represents training in all such methods. If you know it above default, use it instead of the underlying skill whenever you feint (GURPS Basic p. 365) or someone tries to feint you. For instance, with Broadsword at 14 and Feint (Broadsword) at 16, you would make and resist feints at 16.

Feint includes knowledge of Beats (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 100-101) and Ruses (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 101). Make a ST-based roll to attempt a Beat or to use ST to resist one, an IQ-based roll to try a Ruse, or a Per-based roll to use Per to resist a Ruse. To find your level, add the difference between the relevant score and DX to Feint; e.g., DX 12, IQ 14, and Feint at 16 would allow a Ruse at 18.

Some styles include a Style Perk that permits a default to Acrobatics, Dancing, or another non-combat skill; see Feints Using Non-Combat Skills (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 101)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Finger Lock"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Arm Lock-3."
		prereq="Arm Lock; cannot exceed Arm Lock."
		desc="This technique lets you grab fingers and twist them painfully. Use the rules for Arm Lock (GURPS Basic Set, p. 403), except that all damage is to the hand – which is easier to cripple than the arm."
	/>
	<element
		name="Ground Fighting"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-4."
		prereq="Any unarmed combat or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you 'buy off' the -4 for attacking from your back. Roll against this technique instead of the prerequisite skill whenever you use that skill to attack from the ground. For instance, if you had Wrestling-14 and Ground Fighting (Wrestling)-13, you could grapple from the ground at skill 13. In addition, make a roll against Ground Fighting whenever you must defend yourself from your back. On a success, you defend at -1 instead of at -3.

For every two points invested in Ground Fighting, you may also ignore -1 of the -3 to defend from the ground. Ground Fighting at skill-3 or skill-2 means you’re at -2, while at skill-1 or full skill, you have only -1. This replaces the rule on GURPS Basic Set p. 231."
	/>
	<element
		name="Horse Archery"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Bow-4."
		prereq="Bow and Riding; cannot exceed Bow skill."
		desc="This technique lets you use a bow effectively from horseback. The modifiers for firing from horseback (GURPS Basic Set, p. 397) can never reduce your Bow skill below your Horse Archery level. (Other penalties apply normally.) For instance, if you had Bow-13 and Horse Archery-11, the penalties for archery from horseback would never reduce your skill below 11, before other modifiers.

Alternatively, if you're using Martial Arts rules, 'Horse Archery' is shorthand for Mounted Shooting (Bow/Horse). See the Mounted Shooting technique (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 77)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Jump Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Karate-4."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed Karate skill."
		desc="This technique lets you leap into the air and kick at full extension, increasing range and damage. It is a showy but dangerous move! Roll against Jump Kick to hit. Add one yard to reach and +2 to damage. Your target parries at -2. However, if you miss – or if your target successfully defends – you fall down unless you can make a DX-4 or Acrobatics-2 roll. Hit or miss, a Jump Kick leaves you at -2 on all your active defenses until your next turn.

The GURPS Martial Arts alternate is as follows, talk with your GM about what version will they use:

It’s a special option for Committed Attack (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 99-100) and All-Out Attack(GURPS Basic Set, p. 365). The rules below replace the standard ones for those maneuvers.

As a Committed Attack, a Jump Kick involves a short jump forward or sideways that ends in a sharp kick. You must take two steps toward your foe; this effectively gives an extra yard of reach. Roll against Jump Kick to hit. A hit does thrust+1 crushing damage – or thrust at +1 per two dice, if better – plus Karate bonuses. Afterward, you cannot dodge or retreat until next turn, and have -2 on all other active defenses. On a miss, make the usual DX roll to avoid a fall; see GURPS Basic Set p. 274.

An All-Out Attack involves hurling your body at your opponent foot-first. You must move at least half your Move (minimum 2 yards) forward. Roll against Jump Kick to hit.

Your target parries at -2. A hit inflicts thrust+2 – or thrust at +1 per die, if better – plus skill bonuses. If you miss, or if your target successfully defends, you fall down unless you can make a DX-4 or Acrobatics-2 roll. Hit or miss, you have no defenses at all until next turn!

These rules are intended for Martial Arts campaigns. The GM is free to use the less-realistic version on GURPS Basic Set p. 231 in games that don’t focus on the martial arts."
	/>
	<element
		name="Kicking"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-2 or Karate-2."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you improve your kicking ability. Roll against Kicking to hit. A kick does thrust/crushing damage based on ST. Use Brawling or Karate skill – not your Kicking level – to determine your damage bonus, and use only the highest bonus. If you miss with a kick, roll vs. Kicking skill or DX to avoid falling.

Alternatively, if you're following GURPS Martial Arts: Kicking covers all kicks not defined as standalone techniques: crescent kicks, hook kicks, rising kicks, roundhouse kicks, snap kicks, etc. Knowledgeable players are free to embellish, but in all cases, a kick requires an attack roll against Kicking and inflicts thrust crushing damage. Use Brawling or Karate skill – not Kicking – to determine the damage bonus, and use only the highest bonus. If you miss, roll vs. Kicking or DX to avoid falling down.

Combine Kicking with Committed Attack (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 99-100) or All-Out Attack for devastating kicks like roundhouses or stepping side kicks, or with Defensive Attack (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 100) for close, jabbing kicks. Add in Deceptive Attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. 369) for fast snaps and other tricky moves, or Telegraphic Attack (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 113) for slow kicks with big windups."
	/>
	<element
		name="Knee Strike"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Brawling-1 or Karate-1."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you 'buy off' the -1 penalty to strike with the knee – see Knee Strike (GURPS Basic Set, p. 404).

If you’ve grappled your opponent, they defends at -2; if you grappled from the front, you may attack their groin at no penalty! On a hit, roll thrust crushing damage, plus your Brawling or Karate bonus.

Some fighters like to grab an opponent’s head and pull it down into a Knee Strike. For details, see Grab and Smash! (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 118)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Neck Snap"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="ST-4; cannot exceed ST+3"
		prereq="—"
		desc="This brute-force attack consists of grabbing and suddenly twisting the victim’s head, with the intent of snapping the neck – see Neck Snap o Wrench Limb (GURPS Basic Set, p. 404). Unlike most techniques, Neck Snap defaults to ST, not a skill. Wrestling gives its usual skill-based ST bonus.

To use this technique, you must first grapple your opponent by the neck using two hands; see Grappling (GURPS Basic Set, p. 370). Your victim may attempt to break free on their turn. If they fail, then on your next turn, roll a Quick Contest: Neck Snap vs. the higher of their ST or HT. This counts as an attack.

If you win, you inflict swing crushing damage on your victim’s neck, with the usual x1.5 wounding modifier for hit location. The target’s rigid DR protects normally, but flexible armor – including natural DR with the Flexible or Tough Skin limitation – has no effect. Neck injury can have serious consequences; see Lasting and Permanent Injuries (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 138-139).

Otherwise, you inflict no damage. You may make repeated attempts on later turns. Your opponent may attack you or attempt to break free during this time, subject to the usual limitations of being grappled."
	/>
	<element
		name="Acrobatic Stand"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Acrobatics-6."
		prereq="Acrobatics; cannot exceed Acrobatics skill."
		desc="This represents training at quickly regaining your feet in a fight; see Acrobatic Stand (GURPS Basic Set, p. 98) for details. A successful roll lets you go from lying down to standing as a single Change Posture maneuver; on a critical success, you do so as a 'step.' Failure means you go to a sitting posture. Critical failure leaves you lying down, wasting your turn.

You can also use Acrobatic Stand to go from crawling or sitting to standing as a step. In this case, failure means you stand as a Change Posture maneuver, not as a step. Critical failure means you fall down!

Modifiers: A penalty equal to your encumbrance level."
	/>
	<element
		name="Off-Hand Weapon Training"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-4."
		prereq="Any Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you 'buy off' the -4 for using your 'off' hand with one specific Melee Weapon skill. Use your level with this technique instead of the prerequisite skill whenever you use that skill to attack or parry with your off hand. For instance, if you had Rapier-14 and Off-Hand Weapon Training (Rapier)-14, you could attack and parry at full skill with your off hand.

With the GM’s permission, you can learn this technique for any DX-based skill that requires only one hand."
	/>
	<element
		name="Retain Weapon"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill."
		prereq="Any Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill +5."
		desc="If you know this technique above default, you may use it instead of the underlying skill whenever someone attempts to disarm you (see Striking at Weapons, GURPS Basic Set, p. 400). For instance, if you have Staff-13 and Retain Weapon (Staff)-16, you resist disarm attempts as if you had Staff-16.

Should an adversary try to disarm you using brute strength, you may make a ST-based Retain Weapon roll instead of a ST roll. Find your level by subtracting DX and adding ST. For example, if you have ST 14, DX 12, and Retain Weapon-15, your ST-based level is 15 - 12 + 14 = 17.

You can also learn this technique for missile weapons, such as guns and bows. In that case, it defaults to DX and cannot exceed DX+5."
	/>
	<element
		name="Sweep"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-3."
		prereq="Appropriate Melee Weapon or unarmed combat skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you knock down an opponent in a single attack rather than by grappling them and executing a takedown or throw. It isn’t aimed at their center of mass with the goal of pushing them away, like a Push Kick or shove. It’s an attempt to 'clothesline' their neck or head, knock their legs out from under them, or otherwise unbalance them.

Roll against Sweep to hit. Hit location is a special effect – don’t apply a penalty for it. Your target may defend normally. If they fail, roll a Quick Contest: your Sweep or ST vs. their ST, DX, Acrobatics, or best grappling skill. Use the highest value in both cases. If they lose, they fall down.

Many combat skills can Sweep. You can try an armed version with any two-handed weapon with reach 2+. This defaults to Polearm, Spear, Staff, Two-Handed Axe/Mace, Two-Handed Flail, or Two-Handed Sword, and has the weapon’s usual reach. You can also Sweep with Judo, Karate, or Sumo Wrestling. When you attack, specify a stiff arm to the upper body (reach C, requires a free hand), a sweeping kick (reach C, 1, uses a leg), or a pull in a clinch (reach C, only when grappling). Those with Strikers, especially tails, can learn Sweep (Brawling) and attack at their usual reach.

Regardless of the weapon used, Sweep is a slow, pushing attack that doesn’t inflict damage."
	/>
	<element
		name="Whirlwind Attack"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-5."
		prereq="Broadsword, Staff, or Two-Handed Sword; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Whirlwind Attack is a special All-Out Attack that lets you attack every foe adjacent to you with lightning speed! If you use this technique, it is all you can do that turn, no matter how fast or skilled you are. Furthermore, since this is an All-Out Attack, you will have no active defenses afterward – see All-Out Attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. 365).

When you launch a Whirlwind Attack, you spin in place, attacking all adjacent foes within one yard. You must attack them in clockwise or counterclockwise order – your choice. All your attacks must be swung attacks, and you cannot combine a Whirlwind Attack with other techniques (such as Disarming) or with cinematic skills (such as Power Blow).

Determine a random hit location for each target, and then roll against Whirlwind Attack to hit, with the usual hit location penalties. You opponent may defend normally. Resolve each attack completely before moving on to the next one. If any of the attacks is a critical miss (or if any of your opponents critically succeeds on their defense), that attack and all remaining attacks are critical misses – roll on the Critical Miss Table (GURPS Basic Set, p. 556) once per attack!

You may end a Whirlwind Attack facing in any direction you wish."
	/>
	<element
		name="Impersonate"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Mimicry (Speech)-3."
		prereq="Mimicry (Speech); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Through practice, you can improve your ability to mimic one specific person, gradually buying off the -3 to impersonate them. Each person mimicked is a separate technique."
	/>
	<element
		name="Lifesaving"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Swimming-5."
		prereq="Swimming; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="You can study lifesaving separately from swimming in order to eliminate the basic -5 for that task. See Lifesaving (GURPS Basic Set, p. 355) for detailed rules."
	/>
	<element
		name="Motion-Picture Camera"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Photography-3."
		prereq="Photography."
		desc="This technique, common among professional cameramen, allows you to buy off the -3 to use a motion-picture camera with Photography skill."
	/>
	<element
		name="No-Landing Extraction"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Piloting-4."
		prereq="Pilotiong; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you pick up cargo from the ground without landing. You can only fetch cargos outfitted with special no-landing extraction apparatus. Someone on the ground must make a successful Freight Handling roll to prepare the cargo (takes 2d hours). A failed Freight Handling or No-Landing Extraction roll means a missed pick-up or damaged cargo. Critical failure indicates the cargo is lost (critically injured, if a living passenger)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Rope Up"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Climbing-2."
		prereq="Climbing; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="A climber normally has -2 to climb a dangling rope (see Climbing, p. 349). With practice, you can buy off this penalty.

The 'opposite' technique, Rope Down, defaults to Climbing-1 and can be improved to Climbing+3. Sliding down a rope is significantly easier than any kind of climbing!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Rope Down"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Climbing-1."
		prereq="Climbing; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+3."
		desc="A climber normally has -2 to climb a dangling rope (see Climbing, p. 349). With practice, you can buy off this penalty. Sliding down a rope is significantly easier than any kind of climbing!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Scaling"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Climbing-3."
		prereq="Climbing; cannot exceed oprerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you eliminate some or all of the -3 to skill for climbing a relatively smooth, vertical surface such as a building or rock face (see Climbing, p. 349)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Set Trap"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Explosives (Demolition)-2."
		prereq="Explosives (Demolition); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="With study, you can gain familiarity with 'trap' triggers, allowing you to set traps without the usual -2 to skill. Assassins, commandos, spies, etc. often improve this technique."
	/>
	<element
		name="Slip Handcuffs"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Escape-5."
		prereq="Escape; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique represents study of a specific set of tricks for slipping out of handcuffs. With the GM’s permission, you can learn similar techniques for other restraints commonly used in your game world."
	/>
	<element
		name="Work by Touch"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Lockpicking-5."
		prereq="Lockpicking; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Lockpicking is normally at -5 if you must work by touch, but if you routinely practice this way, it will eventually become second nature. The GM might permit you to learn a Work by Touch technique for other 'thief' skills – e.g., Explosives and Traps – allowing you to operate in total darkness, which is a common way to use such skills..."
	/>
	<element
		name="Aggressive Parry"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Parry-1."
		prereq="Boxing, Brawling, or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry."
		desc="Only a few 'hard' styles teach this tactic. Instead of merely deflecting a blow, you attempt to injure your attacker with an especially forceful parry. This is incompatible with Cross Parry (GURPS Basic Set, p. 121).

Roll against Aggressive Parry to defend, at the usual -2 for Boxing vs. a kick, or -3 for Boxing or Brawling vs. a swung weapon. You cannot retreat. Failure means you’re hit; your attacker may choose to hit their original target, your parrying arm, or your parrying hand. Success means you parry and may roll against the underlying skill to strike the attacking body part or weapon, modified as follows.

Modifiers: Against unarmed, -2 to hit an arm or leg, -4 to hit a hand or foot; -2 for Boxing vs. a leg or foot; -1 if your foe knows Rapid Retraction (GURPS Basic Set, p. 51). Against armed, a basic -3; another -3 to -5 for weapon size (see GURPS Basic Set, p. B400); a further -3 for Boxing or Brawling vs. a swung weapon.

Success on this skill roll inflicts thrust-4 crushing damage or thrust-2 at -1 per die, whichever is worse, on the targeted weapon or body part. Skill bonuses apply normally. Failure means you didn’t parry forcefully enough to inflict damage.

Weapon parries against unarmed attacks are essentially aggressive 'for free'; see Parrying Unarmed Attacks (GURPS Basic Set, p. B376)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Armed Grapple"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Cloak, or other prerequisite skill-2."
		prereq="Cloak or appropriate Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Many armed styles teach how to step close to a foe, maneuver a weapon past them, and then pull it in tightly to restrain them. This results in an actual grapple of their body in close combat. To snag an opponent at full reach, use Entangle (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 71) for a flexible weapon or Hook (GURPS Basic Set, p. 74) for one with a hook or other projection. To lock blades with them, use Bind Weapon.

To initiate an armed grapple, roll against weapon skill at -2 – this is an awkward and unconventional attack for most weapons. It’s a standard move with a cloak, however, and uses your unpenalized Cloak skill (see p. B404). Use the hit location penalties for grappling, not those for striking.

Your opponent may use any normal defense. If they fail to defend, you’ve successfully grappled them with your weapon. While using your weapon to grapple, you can neither attack nor defend with it. On your turn, you can follow up with a takedown, pin, choke, or Arm Lock (options depend on the body part grappled). Releasing the grapple is a free action.

A one-handed weapon other than a cloak can only grapple if you grip it in two hands first. This requires a Ready maneuver."
	/>
	<element
		name="Attack from Above"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Prerequisite skill-2."
		prereq="Any unarmed or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Some styles teach techniques for pouncing on a foe from  above. This technique lets you buy off the -2 to attack described in Attack from Above (Basioc Set p. 402). It’s particularly suitable for cinematic ninjas!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Axe Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Karate-4."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed Karate skill."
		desc="This kick involves lifting a leg and smashing it down onto the target heel-first. It’s a special option for Committed Attack (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 99-100) and All-Out Attack (GURPS Basic p. B365). Use the rules below instead of the normal rules for those maneuvers.

An Axe Kick has reduced vertical reach. If your foe’s SM exceeds yours by +1, you can’t target their head while he’s standing. If he’s larger, you can’t hit their head unless he’s crawling or on the ground. Resolve an attack to the foot as a Stamp Kick (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 80-81) rolled at your Axe Kick level.

As a Committed Attack, an Axe Kick does thrust+1 crushing damage – or thrust at +1 per two dice, if better – plus skill bonuses. Roll against Axe Kick to hit. Afterward, you can’t dodge or retreat until next turn, and are at -2 on all remaining active defenses.

As an All-Out Attack, an Axe Kick does thrust+2 – or thrust at +1 per die, if better – plus skill bonuses. Hit or miss, you have no defenses until your next turn!

An Axe Kick is difficult to back away from. If your opponent’s retreat bonus makes the difference between a hit and a miss for an attack aimed above the foot, the kick still hits a lower body part. Head or neck shots strike the torso; torso, arm, or hand blows hit a leg; and kicks to the groin or leg stomp a foot.

This move also beats down the target’s guard. A successful attack roll gives the defender -1 to parry any attack following the Axe Kick until their next turn – even if their defense against the kick succeeds. Axe Kick is a good opener for a Rapid Strike or Combination!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Bind Weapon"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-3."
		prereq="Jitte/Sai or any fencing weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Fencers with swords that have crosspiece hilts can lock blades or hilts in a so-called bind. With a pronged weapon such as the jitte (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 217), it’s possible to bind any weapon. This technique covers all such tactics.

To bind, you must first successfully parry your opponent’s fencing blade with your own such sword – or use a Jitte/Sai weapon to parry any weapon. On your first turn after the parry, roll against Bind Weapon to try to bind the weapon you parried; this is an attack. If you’re using a fencing weapon, your adversary must be within a yard and you must step into close combat. With a Jitte/Sai weapon, the target weapon must merely be in reach (GURPS Basic Set, p. 400).

Your foe’s only legal defenses are a dodge or a parry with the targeted weapon. They may retreat for the usual bonus. If their defense fails, you bind weapons – and if they tried to retreat, they can’t step back.

You can use Bind Weapon offensively rather than after a parry. Step into range (see above) and roll against Bind Weapon to hit. The only difference is that your foe may try any defense, not just a dodge or a parry with the target weapon.

While a bind is in effect, neither fighter can use the weapons involved to attack or defend. All other actions taken by defender and attacker alike are at -2 DX.

Your foe may attempt to free their weapon on their turn. This counts as an attempt to break free (GURPS Basic p. 371), and requires a full turn and a Quick Contest of their weapon skill against your Bind Weapon technique. If they use finesse to disengage, make DX-based rolls. If they use brute force, the rolls are ST-based. If they win, the bind ends – and if they used ST, you must make a skill or Retain Weapon roll or drop the weapon you used to bind!

Either of you can escape by dropping the weapon in the bind. This is a free action at any time. You can end the bind without losing your weapon. This, too, is a free action – but only on your turn.

This tactic is common for two-weapon fencers – especially those with a main-gauche. The objective is to bind the enemy’s blade and attack with a secondary weapon. Jitte/Sai fighters use paired weapons to similar effect."
	/>
	<element
		name="Breakfall"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Acrobatics, Judo, or Wrestling."
		prereq="Acrobatics, Judo, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+5."
		desc="This technique covers ways of controlling or absorbing the shock of a fall: shoulder rolls, slapping the ground, and so on. When you’re thrown for damage (see Judo Throw, GURPS Martial Arts, p. 75), a successful Breakfall roll deducts one plus your margin of success from damage. If this prevents all damage, you may opt to end up crouching instead of lying down. You can also try to end up crouching after a non-damaging throw, but the lack of momentum makes it tricky: roll at Breakfall-3. Finally, you may substitute Breakfall for Acrobatics when rolling to reduce the effective distance of a fall (See Falling, GURPS Basic Set p. B431); any success lets you end up crouching, if you wish."
	/>
	<element
		name="Cavalry Training"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Malee Weapon skill-2."
		prereq="Riding and any Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed Melee Weapon skill."
		desc="This technique lets a mounted warrior buy off the -2 for attacking on the same turn as their mount (see Attacks by Mounts, GURPS Basic Set p. 397). It also helps when they attack while their mount’s velocity is 7 or more relative to their target. Such an attack is normally at +1 to damage and -1 to skill (see Cavalry Weapons, GURPS Basic Set p. 397), but improving Cavalry Training to Melee Weapon skill-1 eliminates this -1. Raising Cavalry Training to full skill eliminates both penalties. Remember that skill with a mounted attack can’t exceed Riding skill – or Combat Riding, if better."
	/>
<element
	name="Cavalry Training (Guns)"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Guns-2."
	prereq="Riding and Guns; cannot exceed Guns."
	desc="This technique lets a cavalryman buy off the -2 for attacking on a turn when his mount attacks (GURPS Basic Set, p. 397). In addition, improving Cavalry Training to skill-1 lets him use only half his mount’s speed when assessing speed/range penalties, where favorable, while improving it to full skill means only target speed matters. Skill with a mounted attack can’t exceed Riding skill – or Combat Riding (below), if better – and modifiers for a rough ride require Mounted Shooting (GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 44)."
/>
	<element
		name="Close Combat"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-4, -8, or -12."
		prereq="Any Melee Weapon skill; cannot remove more than half the default penality."
		desc="In close combat (GURPS Basic Set, p. 391), a weapon without 'C' in its Reach statistic gives a skill penalty based on its reach: -4 for reach 1, -8 for reach 2, or -12 for reach 3. In addition, swing damage is at -1 per yard of reach; e.g., a broadsword does -1 damage, a greatsword gets -2, and a full-sized halberd has -3. Thrusting attacks do normal damage. Calculate skill and swing damage penalties using the weapon’s longest reach, not the reach at which it’s currently ready.

This technique lets you buy off half the skill penalty. You may buy it up to skill-2 for a reach 1 weapon, skill-4 for a reach 2 weapon, or skill-6 for a reach 3 weapon.

All of this assumes a normal grip. See Reversed Grip (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 111-112) for an alternative. Hilt punches and the like use Pummeling (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 111) instead of these rules; this technique doesn’t apply.

Close Combat is also available for ranged weapons. This lets you buy off the entire Bulk penalty for close-combat purposes only; see Weapons for Close Combat (GURPS Basic Set, p. 391). Those with Heroic Archer (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 45) don’t need this technique."
	/>
	<element
		name="Combat Riding"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Riding"
		prereq="Riding; cannot exceed Riding+4"
		desc="This technique represents training at riding under combat conditions. Use it instead of Riding whenever you roll to control your mount in battle. It doesn’t cover fighting – for that, learn Cavalry Training or Mounted Shooting (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 77) – but where the rules limit weapon skill to Riding, your limit is Combat Riding instead. Combat Riding never aids Riding rolls to mount up, stay mounted, or direct your mount hands-free – see Hands-Free Riding (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 73), Quick Mount (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 78), and Staying Seated (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 81) for those tricks – or for such non-combat activities as dressage, racing, and travel."
	/>
	<element
		name="Counterattack"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-5."
		prereq="Any unarmed combat or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Counterattack represents attacking as soon as possible after defending in order to take advantage of the momentary 'hole' an attacker must leave in their defenses. You can only attempt it on your turn immediately following a successful active defense – and only vs. the foe against whom you defended. If they blocked or parried, the Counterattack doesn’t have to use the hand(s) you used to defend, although it can if you wish. 

Roll against Counterattack to hit. Your foe is at -2 to Parry, or to their resistance roll if you tried a grappling move that uses a Quick Contest (e.g., takedown), or at -1 to Block or Dodge. If you hit, your attack inflicts its usual damage.

You can use another technique as your counterattack; see Using Techniques Together (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 64) to find effective skill level."
	/>
	<element
		name="Crack"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Whip-4."
		prereq="Whip; cannot exceed Whip skill."
		desc="You can 'crack' any ordinary whip – this is the sound of the tip breaking the sound barrier! Such an attack is at -4 to skill but +2 to damage. Crack lets you buy off the skill penalty. In a cinematic (or silly) campaign, Crack might work with anything whip-like: ropes, belts, long braids, wet towels..."
	/>
	<element
		name="Drop Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-1, Sumo Wrestling-1, or Wrestling-2."
		prereq="Brawling, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This attack uses two feet in an attempt to injure and knock down an opponent. It’s a special option for Move and Attack. Use the following rules instead of the normal rules for that maneuver.

A Drop Kick is a type of slam (GURPS Basic Set, p. 371). You must move at least a yard towards your target. The kick itself has a reach of 2 yards. Roll against Drop Kick to hit. Damage is as for a slam, at +2 for going feet first (or +3 if wearing heavy boots). Brawling, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling adds its usual damage bonus. Succeed or fail, you immediately fall down. Until your next turn, you may block or parry from the ground at the usual penalties, but you can’t dodge or retreat. In a cinematic game, GMs may allow an Acrobatics-5 roll for the attacker to land on their feet after a successful Drop Kick. A miss results in a fall!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Ear Clap"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Boxing-3, Brawling-3, or Karate-3."
		prereq="Boxing, Brawling, or Karate, cannot exceed prerequisite skill-1."
		desc="This is an attack on your foe’s ear using a cupped or open hand. The goal is to pop their eardrum, stunning and deafening them. You must be in close combat and have at least one free, empty hand.

Roll against Ear Clap to hit. Your opponent may use any active defense. If the attack succeeds, it does thrust-3 crushing damage plus skill bonuses. In addition, roll a Quick Contest: Ear Clap vs. the victim’s HT. If you win, your target is physically stunned (GURPS Basic Set, p. 420); they’re also at -1 DX and deaf in one ear (treat as Hard of Hearing) for 1d seconds. On a critical failure on the HT roll or critical success on Ear Clap, the victim must roll as if for a crippling injury to see how long they’re partially deaf; see GURPS Basic Set, p. 422. Permanent harm is possible!

Ear Clap works best if you box both ears simultaneously. To do a double Ear Clap, you must have two free, empty hands and use All-Out Attack (Double) or another form of multiple attacks. Dual-Weapon Attack with the appropriate unarmed combat skill is one option; add the penalties for that technique to Ear Clap to determine effective skill. If only one hand hits, resolve it as above. If both hit, roll one Quick Contest. If you win, your victim is deaf in both ears (treat as Deafness) for 2d seconds. Once again, a critical failure on HT or critical success on Ear Clap indicates a crippling injury that could become permanent."
	/>
	<element
		name="Elbow Drop"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-4 or Wrestling-5."
		prereq="Brawling or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This is a devastating elbow strike delivered using the whole body. It’s normally done by dropping from a standing posture, driving an elbow into the victim and landing on top of them. You can use it against a kneeling, sitting, or lying foe, making it an ideal follow-up to a takedown. Elbow Drop is a special option for Committed Attack or All-Out Attack. Use the rules here instead of the usual ones for those maneuvers. Roll against Elbow Drop to hit. The victim may dodge or block, or parry at -2. If they parry, your body counts as a weapon with weight equal to your ST; see Parrying Heavy Weapons (GURPS Basic Set, p. 376).

As a Committed Attack, Elbow Drop inflicts thrust+2, or thrust at +1 per die if better. Brawling adds its usual damage bonus; Wrestling adds damage equal to its ST bonus (+1 at DX+1, +2 at DX+2 or better) instead. As an All-Out Attack, damage is thrust+3, or thrust-1 at +2 per die if better, plus skill bonuses. If an Elbow Drop causes knockback, the target goes nowhere – but if they’re sitting or kneeling, they must make the usual DX roll or be knocked down.

If you miss, you hit the ground and suffer the damage you would have inflicted. The same thing happens if your opponent blocks with a shield.

Succeed or fail, you end up lying face-up on the ground. After a Committed Attack, you’re at -2 to defend and unable to retreat. After an All-Out Attack, you’re defenseless!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Entangle"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Kusari-4 or Whip-4."
		prereq="Kusari or Whip; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="You can use a flexible weapon such as a whip or a kusari to entangle a foe. Roll against Entangle to hit. If your opponent fails to defend, the weapon wraps around them.

If you hit your victim’s arm or torso, you ensnare it. On subsequent turns, you must take a Ready maneuver to keep your opponent snared. Roll a Quick Contest of ST each turn. If you win, you immobilize your foe. If you lose, they pull your weapon from your grasp. On a tie, they immediately break free without disarming you.

If you entangle the neck, use the same rules but your opponent has -5 in the Contest. If you win, the whip or kusari cuts off the victim’s breathing – see Suffocation (GURPS Basic Set, p. 436).

If you entangle a foot or a leg, the target must make a DX roll to remain standing (this is instead of the Contest above). They’re at -4 if they were running. If they fall, they take 1d-4 crushing damage – or 1d-2 if running. On subsequent turns, use the rules above to keep them entangled.

You must keep your weapon taut at all times to immobilize or suffocate your victim. This requires a Ready maneuver each turn. If you’re mounted and your mount is trained to do this for you, substitute its ST for yours in the Quick Contest.

To escape from a taut whip or kusari, you must attack and cut it (the damage required depends on the weapon). To escape from a limp weapon – including one pulled from the attacker’s grasp – you need a free hand and must make three successful DX rolls. Each attempt counts as a Ready maneuver, during which you may take no other action."
	/>
	<element
		name="Evade"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Acrobatics or Judo."
		prereq="Acrobatics or Judo; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+5."
		desc="This technique represents training at avoiding opponents who wish to obstruct your movement. Evade (Acrobatics) lets you flip over, tumble under, or twist around your foe, while Evade (Judo) allows you to ward off your enemy’s hands as you run past. Either replaces DX when trying to evade (see Evading, GURPS Basic Set, p. 368). All normal penalties apply."
	/>
	<element
		name="Exotic Hand Strike"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Karate-1."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed Karate skill."
		desc="Certain hand strikes use unusual striking surfaces: the edge of the hand, a single protruding knuckle, a clawshaped fist, etc. These do extra damage to fleshy or fragile targets at the cost of being much more vulnerable to injury when striking a hard surface such as armor or bone. Roll against Exotic Hand Strike to hit. Standard hit location penalties apply. Damage is thrust crushing plus Karate bonuses. Hurting Yourself (GURPS Basic Set, p. 379) applies if your target has any DR – not just DR 3+."
	/>
	<element
		name="Eye-Gouging"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-5, Judo-5, or Wrestling-5"
		prereq="Brawling, Judo, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This close-combat attack consists of grabbing someone’s head and pressing your thumbs into their eyes. It usually requires two empty hands. Roll against Eye-Gouging to hit.

Your foe may defend normally. If they fail, you grapple them and they cannot see! They can try to break free (GURPS Basic Set, p. B371) as usual on their turn.

Until your victim breaks free, you can drive your thumbs into their eyes on subsequent turns. This counts as an attack but doesn’t require an attack roll. Each eye takes thrust-4 crushing damage. This can cripple and blind the eyes but never gets the x4 wounding modifier for the skull – the thumbs are too short! (Exception: The GM may give some nonhumans the perk 'Long Thumbs,' in which case the wounding modifier does apply. The same goes for fighters with Talons or Long Talons.)

You can gouge one-handed. The attack roll is against Eye-Gouging-4. Only one eye takes damage on later turns."
	/>
	<element
		name="Eye-Pluck"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-10 or Karate-10."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed pre-requisite skill-4."
		desc="This cinematic technique involves using the clawed fingers of one hand to grab an enemy’s eye and pull it out. It’s a strike, not a grapple. You can try it repeatedly but you can’t 'hold onto' your enemy’s eye. Roll against Eye-Pluck to hit.

Damage is thrust-3 crushing, plus your Brawling or Karate bonus. Injury over HP/10 cripples the eye. Any excess is lost. The difference between this and Eye-Poke is that if you cripple the eye, your victim must make an immediate HT roll. Failure means you pluck out their eye – a permanent crippling injury! See GURPS Basic Set p. 422.

If your foe’s Size Modifier exceeds yours by +5 or more, their eye is too big for you to grab and your Eye-Pluck counts only as an Eye-Poke."
	/>
	<element
		name="Eye-Poke"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Boxing-9, Brawling-9, or Karate-9."
		prereq="Boxing, Brawling, or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill-4."
		desc="This is a jab to the eye using an extended finger. It can blind but it never gets the x4 wounding modifier for the skull (compare Lethal Eye-Poke). Roll against Eye-Poke to hit.

A hit inflicts thrust-3 crushing damage. Injury over HP/10 cripples the eye. Any excess is lost. A miss by 1 strikes the protective bone around the eye, damaging the face instead – but as you’re hitting bone, skull DR (usually DR 2) protects. Hurting Yourself (GURPS Basic Set, p. 379) applies if your target has any DR, not just DR 3+, or if you hit bone.

Due to the risk of finger injury, many fighters pull this blow (see Subduing a Foe, GURPS Basic Set p. 401). Little damage is needed to cripple an eye in any event!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Eye-Rake"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-5 or Karate-5."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique attempts to blind the foe by scratching a clawed hand across their face and eyes. It’s easier than most strikes to the eyes because you’re using a broad striking surface against a large target (the upper face), but actual injury is superficial at best.

On a successful hit, roll thrust-1 crushing damage. However, this isn’t a hard strike and normally inflicts no injury. Instead, the victim must make a HT roll at a penalty equal to the damage that penetrates DR. Failure means they’re blinded for 1 minute times their margin of failure. Critical failure means one eye suffers HP/10 of real injury (round down) and is crippled!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Lethal Eye-Poke"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Karate-11."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed Karate-5."
		desc="This is an attempt to drive an extended finger through an eye socket and into the brain. Treat it as Targeted Attack (Karate Lethal Strike/Eye) for all purposes. It inflicts thrust-2 piercing damage, plus Karate bonuses. It can blind and gets the x4 wounding modifier for the skull – just like any other piercing attack. With sufficient damage, it can kill."
	/>
	<element
		name="Hammer Fist"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Brawling-1 or Karate-1."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="A 'hammer fist' is a punch using the side of a clenched fist. This technique includes both the true hammer fist and similar attacks meant to prevent injury to the attacker at the cost of less damage to the target: forearm smashes, punches with the palm or heel of an open hand, etc. In all cases, the striking surface is larger and less rigid than for a normal fist, reducing damage – but it’s much harder to injure your-self, making this strike ideal for hard targets.

Roll against Hammer Fist to hit. Damage is thrust-2 plus skill bonuses. If Hurting Yourself (GURPS Basic Set, p. 379) would apply, damage is 1/10 of what you roll, not 1/5. Furthermore, you suffer a point less damage if your hand is parried aggressively or with a weapon, or otherwise stopped painfully.

If your hand is crippled, you may use Hammer Fist to deliver a forearm smash. Use the above rules, but any self-inflicted injury affects the arm instead of the hand."
	/>
	<element
		name="Handcuffing"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Binding, DX-2, Judo-1, or Wrestling-2; cannot exceed Binding, DX, Judo, or Wrestling."
		prereq="—"
		desc="This is a limited, realistic version of Binding (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 82-83) for handcuffing a target quickly. It only works in close combat – and only if you grappled your target on a previous turn or parried their melee attack immediately prior to your turn.

On your turn, roll a Quick Contest: Handcuffing vs. the higher of your victim’s DX or best grappling skill. This counts as an attack. Victory means you’ve handcuffed a limb of your choice. On later turns, you can repeat the process to cuff another limb or make an uncontested Handcuffing roll to attach the cuff to an inanimate object (pole, car door, bomb...) within a yard.

You can handcuff a pinned opponent automatically in 2d seconds. A successful, unopposed Handcuffing roll reduces this to two seconds (one second on a critical success).

Escape attempts use the Escape skill (GURPS Basic Set, p. 192) or Slip Handcuffs technique (GURPS Basic Set, p. 233). This takes a minute. Time reductions give the usual penalties; see Time Spent (GURPS Basic Set, p. 346). The GM may permit cinematic heroes one attempt at -10 to escape in a turn – effectively instantly."
	/>
	<element
		name="Hands-Free Riding"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Riding-3."
		prereq="Riding; cannot exceed Riding skill."
		desc="Using only one hand to control your mount gives -1 to all Riding rolls, while using no hands at all gives -3; see Mounted Combat (GURPS Basic Set, p. 396). This technique represents training to buy off these penalties. Roll against Hands-Free Riding instead of Riding to control your mount using no hands. If you’ve improved this technique at all, you may ignore the -1 for using only one hand."
	/>
	<element
		name="Head Butt"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-1 or Karate-1"
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This is a close-combat strike using the forehead. Natural targets are the face (-5) and skull (-7) of a standing adversary, but you can attack anything! However, while the skull is hard, it has poor reach and leverage for striking.

Roll against Head Butt to hit. Damage is thrust-1 crushing. Your victim may defend normally; if they parry, any damage this causes affects your face. Self-inflicted injury for a target with DR 3+ applies to the skull; however, your skull’s DR 2 protects normally. If you have rigid head protection – e.g., a metal helm – add +1 to damage and apply your armor’s DR against self-inflicted injury.

Head Butt requires practice to be effective; fighters without Brawling or Karate strike at DX-2 and do only thrust-2 damage. This move is sometimes used while grappling and (illegally) in boxing matches, but it doesn’t benefit from Boxing, Judo, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling. Races with Strikers (GURPS Basic Set, p. 88) on their head don’t need Head Butt – they attack at full skill and do superior damage."
	/>
	<element
		name="Head Lock"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Judo-3 or Wrestling-3."
		prereq="Judo or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This attack involves controlling an enemy’s head and neck using two arms. It targets similar body parts to Choke Hold (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 69). However, the goal is to lock your victim’s neck in a way that lets you injure it or their throat – not to cut off their blood or air supply.

To apply this lock, you must first grapple your opponent by the neck; see Grappling (GURPS Basic Set, p. 370). Your victim may attempt to break free on their turn. If they fail, then on your next turn, you have two ways to injure them: you may attempt to choke them as described under Choke or Strangle (GURPS Basic Set, p. 370), substituting Head Lock for ST if better, or you may try to throw them as explained in Throws from Locks (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 118-119). You can alternate between these attacks for as long as you maintain the lock.

Treat sports-wrestling locks that seek to avoid causing injury as simple head or neck grapples. The same goes for the so-called head lock seen on the street (an arm around the neck)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Hook"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-5."
		prereq="Any appropriate Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This is the technique of using a weapon with a projection – usually a hook – to snag a foe’s head, limb, weapon, or shield in order to pull them off-balance. You can learn it for any Melee Weapon skill, but you’ll need a suitable weapon to use it.

Hook is a common technique for Axe/Mace, Polearm, and Two-Handed Axe/Mace, but while picks and most axes can hook, maces and knobbed clubs can’t – and only a few polearms sport hooks. It’s possible to add hooks to weapons that normally lack them, such as spears and staffs. Some swordfighting schools even taught (gauntleted!) fighters to grab their weapon by the blade and hook with the pommel and crosspiece. Swords wielded this way use the Axe/Mace or Two-Handed Axe/Mace skill, and are unbalanced. See GURPS Martial Arts Chapter 6 for more on suitable weapons and the associated skills.

Roll against Hook to hit, modified for the target as noted below. Your adversary may defend normally. Hook doesn’t usually inflict damage, but some weapons have an edged hook. While using a weapon to hook a foe, you can’t use it to attack or parry. You can always release or drop it as a free action on your turn, however.

If hooking the head or a limb, apply standard hit location penalties. If you succeed, then on subsequent turns you may attempt to pull your victim off-balance or even to the ground. Roll a Quick Contest of ST. If you win, you drag your opponent into a kneeling posture; if they’re kneeling or crouching, they fall down. They can’t stand until they break free or you release them. If you lose or tie, nothing happens. If you critically fail, you drop your weapon! Your foe may try to break free normally on their turn.

Hooking a weapon is an attempt to disarm; see GURPS Basic Set p. 401. Apply the usual penalty to hit the weapon but ignore the -2 for a non-fencing weapon. You get +2 in the ensuing Quick Contest, in addition to the usual modifiers. If you lose the Contest, your opponent retains their weapon and escapes from your hook.

If hooking a shield, roll to hit at -4 plus its DB. If you succeed, you may attempt to pull it out of line. Treat this as an attempt to disarm, but your opponent gets +4 in the Quick Contest if their shield is strapped to their arm. You get +2 if hooking with a two-handed weapon. If you win, the shield becomes unready – it’s still on your foe’s arm but they can’t block with it or benefit from its DB until they break free and take a Ready maneuver to reorient it.

Certain weapons designed for hooking are sharpened on the inside of the hook. These include the Chinese hook sword and the European bill. Such weapons inflict the damage listed for their hook in addition to the above effects. If using the optional Pain and Breaking Free rule (p. 119), such weapons are very effective against lightly armored foes!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Jam"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Parry-1."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry."
		desc="A Jam is an attempt to parry a low-line attack – typically a kick – by interposing a foot or leg aggressively enough to injure the attacker. It’s only useful against attacks on your lower body (feet, legs, or groin). You may attempt it instead of a non-damaging leg or foot parry once per turn; see Parries with Legs or Feet (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 123).

Roll against Jam to defend, at the usual -3 for Brawling vs. a swung weapon. You cannot retreat. Failure means you’re hit; your attacker may choose to hit their original target, your parrying leg, or your parrying foot. Success means you parry and may roll against the underlying skill to strike the attacking body part or weapon, modified as follows.

Modifiers: The usual -2 for kicking. Against unarmed, +0 to hit a leg, -2 to hit an arm or foot, -4 to hit a hand; -1 if your foe knows Rapid Retraction (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 51). Against armed, a basic -3; another -3 to -5 for weapon size (see p. B400); a further -3 for Brawling vs. a swung weapon.

Success on this skill roll inflicts thrust-3 crushing damage or thrust-1 at -1 per die, whichever is worse, on the targeted weapon or body part. Skill bonuses apply normally. Failure means you didn’t parry forcefully enough to inflict damage."
	/>
	<element
		name="Judo Throw"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Judo."
		prereq="Judo; cannot exceed Judo skill."
		desc="This is the primary attack of the Judo skill. On the turn immediately after a successful Judo parry, you may attempt to throw your attacker if they’re within a yard. You must have at least one hand free to do so. This counts as an attack. Roll vs. Judo to hit. (On an All-Out Attack, you can’t try two throws but you can make one attempt at +4.) Your foe may use any active defense – they can parry your hand with a weapon! If their defense fails, you throw them.

A thrown foe falls where you please. On a battle map, they land in any two hexes near you. One of these hexes must be their starting hex, your hex, or any hex adjacent to one of those hexes. Your victim must roll against HT. Failure means they’re stunned. If you throw them into someone else, that person must roll vs. the higher of ST+3 or DX+3 to avoid being knocked down.

The intent of Judo Throw is normally to put your rival on the ground – not to injure them – but you can throw them in a way that maximizes the impact of the fall on a specific location, injuring it. This is frowned upon in sport matches! Treat a damaging throw like any other, but at -1 to hit plus any hit location penalty (not halved for grappling). Any location but the eye, vitals, or groin is valid; common targets are the skull, neck, and arm. Damage is thrust-1 crushing; there’s no bonus for skill. The victim may attempt a Breakfall (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 68-69) roll to reduce injury. Other effects are as for a regular Judo Throw.

You may also throw a grappled foe. Instead of parrying first, you must grapple your opponent. On a later turn, try to throw them. This is an attack resolved as a Quick Contest: Judo vs. the highest of your adversary’s ST, DX, or best grappling skill. If you attempt a damaging throw, the extra penalties do modify your roll. If you win, you throw your victim as above. Otherwise, you don’t – but unless you critically fail, you retain your grapple and may try again on a future turn."
	/>
	<element
		name="Knee Drop"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-3 or Wrestling-4."
		prereq="Brawling or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This brutal attack involves dropping your entire weight onto your foe knee-first. It’s normally executed from a standing posture by driving your knee into your adversary and landing on top of them. You can only use it against an opponent who’s lying down, but it’s an ideal follow-up to a take-down. Knee Drop is a special option for Committed Attack or All-Out Attack. Use these rules instead of the usual ones for those maneuvers.

Roll against Knee Drop to hit. Your victim may dodge or block, or parry at -2. If they parry, your body counts as a weapon with weight equal to your ST; see Parrying Heavy Weapons (GURPS Basic Set, p. 376).

As a Committed Attack, Knee Drop inflicts thrust+2, or thrust at +1 per die if better. Brawling adds its usual damage bonus; Wrestling adds damage equal to its ST bonus (+1 at DX+1, +2 at DX+2 or better) instead. As an All-Out Attack, damage is thrust+3, or thrust+1 at +1 per die if better, plus skill bonuses.

On a miss, you hit the ground and one leg takes the damage you would have inflicted. If your opponent blocks with a shield, it has the same effect.

Succeed or fail, you end up kneeling. You’re at -2 to defend and unable to retreat after a Committed Attack. After an All-Out Attack, you’re defenseless!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Leg Grapple"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX, Wrestling, or Judo; cannot exceed DX+4, Wrestling+4, or Judo+4."
		prereq="—"
		desc="Leg Grapple is an attempt to catch the leg of a kicking foe. It’s a common response to high kicks. To use it, you must have one hand free and successfully parry a kick to your upper body – skull, eye, face, neck, torso, vitals, arm, or hand.

On your first turn following the parry, you may attempt to capture your opponent’s leg if they’re within a yard. This is an attack. Step into close combat and roll against Leg Grapple to hit. Your foe can only dodge; this represents retracting their kick before you can catch them. If you succeed, you’ve grabbed their leg.

Your foe may attempt to break free (GURPS Basic Set, p. 371) on their next turn, but you’re at +4 in the Quick Contest. Most fighters follow this technique with Leg Lock or a takedown (GURPS Basic Set, p. 370). If you try a takedown, you’re at +3 in the Quick Contest.

This technique is frowned upon in competition – and often outright illegal in the ring – but very common in street fights. If the campaign emphasizes high-kicking cinematic warriors, the GM may not want to let fighters improve Leg Grapple."
	/>
	<element
		name="Leg Lock"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Judo or Wrestling."
		prereq="Judo or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		desc="A leg lock is an attempt to restrain or cripple an opponent by twisting their leg. This technique allows you to improve your effective Judo or Wrestling skill for this purpose only.

To use Leg Lock, you must have two hands free and already have a successful Leg Grapple (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 76) on your opponent. On your first turn following the Leg Grapple, you may attempt to place your foe’s leg in a lock. This is an attack. Roll against Leg Lock to hit. Your victim may use any active defense – they can parry your hand with a weapon! If their defense fails, you trap their leg in a lock.

Your foe may attempt to break free (GURPS Basic Set, p. B371) on their next turn. If they lose, they have a cumulative -1 on future attempts to break free.

On your next turn – and each turn thereafter, until your opponent breaks free – you may try to damage the trapped leg. Roll a Quick Contest: the higher of your ST (including your Wrestling bonus) or Leg Lock vs. the higher of your victim’s ST+4 or HT+4. If you win, you inflict crushing damage equal to your margin of victory. The target’s rigid DR protects normally. Flexible armor, including natural DR with the Flexible or Tough Skin limitation, has no effect.

If you cripple your victim’s leg, they’ll be unable to stand on it. You can inflict no further damage on a crippled limb, but you can continue to roll the Contest each turn. If you win, your target suffers shock and stunning just as if you had inflicted damage.

Rolls to inflict damage are completely passive and don’t count as attacks. You can simultaneously make close-combat attacks on your opponent, who defends at -4 in addition to any penalties due to the damage caused by the lock itself. An attempt to throw them using the lock does count as an attack; see Throws from Locks (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 118-119).

You can also apply this technique offensively. You must first use Judo or Wrestling to grapple your victim’s leg with two hands. If they fail to break free on their next turn, you may try Leg Lock on your next turn.

Leg Lock uses finesse to cripple a foe’s limb. For a brute-force technique, see Wrench (Limb) (GURPS Basic Set, p. 82)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Low Fighting"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-2."
		prereq="Any combat skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique lets you buy off the -2 to attack from a kneeling or crouching posture. Roll against Low Fighting instead of the prerequisite skill whenever you use that skill to attack from a low posture. For instance, if you had Wrestling at 14 and Low Fighting (Wrestling) at 13, you could grapple from your knees at skill 13.

Low Fighting affects the -2 to defend while kneeling in the same way. If you know it at skill-1, you’re at -1 to defend, while at full skill, you have no penalty."
	/>
	<element
		name="Low-Line Defense"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Parry-2."
		prereq="Boxing or Sumo Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry."
		desc="Kicking is illegal in the boxing or sumo ring, so boxers and sumotori don’t normally train to face it – which is why Boxing and Sumo Wrestling parries are at -2 against kicks. Fighters who cross-train against kicking martial artists or use their skills outside the ring can certainly learn to parry kicks, however! This technique lets them buy off the -2."
	/>
	<element
		name="Mounted Shooting"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Ranged weapon skill-4."
		prereq="Riding or a vehicle-operation skill (Bicycling, Driving, Teamster, etc.), and a ranged weapon skill; cannot exceed ranged weapon skill."
		desc="You’ve practiced shooting a ranged weapon from a moving mount or vehicle – chariot, horse, howdah, etc. You must specialize by both weapon skill and mount or vehicle type. Use the specialties listed for the two skills chosen as prerequisites. Mounted Shooting (Bow/Horse) is extremely common and called 'Horse Archery' for brevity (GURPS Basic Set, p. 231).

If you’ve improved this technique, modifiers for a rough ride and/or limited mobility (see Attacking from Moving Vehicle or Mount, GURPS Basic Set p. 548) – including those for turning in the saddle to shoot – can’t reduce your weapon skill below your Mounted Shooting level when using your chosen weapon from the specified platform. Other penalties apply normally. For instance, if you had Thrown Weapon (Spear)-13 and Mounted Shooting (Thrown Spear/Chariot)-11, the penalties for a bumpy chariot ride couldn’t reduce Thrown Weapon (Spear) below 11, before other modifiers.

Remember that your skill with a mounted attack can’t exceed Riding skill (GURPS Basic Set, p. 397) or Driving, Piloting, or Teamster (for a vehicle). Combat Riding (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 69) mitigates this for the rider themself, but their passengers are limited by their Riding skill.

Mounted forces, such as cavalry troopers, train to shoot from a horse or motorcycle. Bodyguards, SWAT teams, and hostage rescue units learn to fire from a moving car – some American police agencies have been doing so since the 1920s! Ordinary draft troops or civilian shooters will seldom learn this technique.

† The GM may allow Mounted Shooting with other skills involving device-assisted movement; e.g., Parachuting."
	/>
	<element
		name="Push Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-3 or Karate-3."
		prereq="Karate or Brawling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This is a kick that shoves your adversary away instead of injuring them. You hit them with the flat of your foot and push. Many kickboxing styles use this technique to shove an opponent into the ropes or far enough away to allow a full-extension finishing move.

A Push Kick is a shove (GURPS Basic Set, p. 372) in all respects except that it’s done as a kick. Roll against Push Kick to hit. Your opponent may defend normally. If you succeed, roll your usual kicking damage and double it. This damage causes no injury – use it only to work out knockback (GURPS Basic Set, p. 378).

The above rules assume a Push Kick to the torso. A Push Kick to the leg gives the victim -2 to any DX roll to avoid falling down as a result of knockback. Targeting the skull, face, or neck makes the penalty -3. No other hit locations are valid"
	/>
	<element
		name="Quick Mount"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Acrobatics-3, Jumping-3, or Riding-3."
		prereq="Acrobatics, Jumping, or Riding; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique represents training at quickly mounting a horse or similar beast. Roll against it instead of Acrobatics, Jumping, or Riding for this purpose. See Mounting Up (GURPS Basic Set, p. 396).

The GM may allow Quick Mount for motorcycles and even cars (a speedy slide through an open window into the driver or passenger’s seat). This technique requires Acrobatics, Jumping, or the appropriate Driving skill."
	/>
	<element
		name="Return Strike"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Flail-5 or Kusari-5."
		prereq="Flail or Kusari; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique capitalizes on a kusari or flail’s flexibility to strike the enemy from behind while facing them. To attempt it, you must have sufficient reach to attack a yard beyond your opponent – that is, reach equal to their range from you plus a yard.

Roll against Return Strike to hit. If the target has never seen this move (GM decides), treat it as an attack from behind. This usually allows no active defense! Otherwise, it’s considered an attack from the side, which gives -2 to most defenses. See GURPS Basic Set, p. 390-391 for detailed rules. Damage is unchanged, but only the DR on your victim’s back applies.

You can combine Return Strike with Close Combat (GURPS Martial Art p. 69) to do a 'wrap shot' while in close quarters; see Using Techniques Together (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 64). Treat this as striking into close combat (GURPS Basic Set, p. 392). If you miss your target or they dodge, you may hit yourself!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Reverse Grip"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Prerequisite skill-6 for most one-handed weapons, skill-4 for two-handed ones, or full skill for Tonfa (only)."
		prereq="Any Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique – useful only with weapons that can make thrusting attacks – lets you avoid the need for a Ready maneuver to switch between a regular overhand grip and an underhand grip more suitable for close-quarters stabbing. A successful Reverse Grip roll lets you change grips instantly. Failure means you drop the weapon and your turn ends... and critical failure also inflicts Tip Slash (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 113) damage on your torso!

Once reversed, most weapons work differently – see Reversed Grip (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 111-112) for details. The main uses for this technique are to prepare a long weapon for close combat and to sheathe your weapon more quickly (see Quick Sheathing, GURPS Marial Arts p. 102).

You can also use this technique to spin a tonfa (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 225). It defaults to full Tonfa skill, as the weapon’s side handle makes this move exceptionally easy."
	/>
	<element
		name="Sacrifice Throw"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Judo."
		prereq="Judo; cannot exceed prerequisite skill level."
		desc="This technique involves grappling your opponent, falling with them, and using your entire weight to throw them. It’s risky, but difficult to resist. You may only attempt it if a regular Judo Throw (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 75) would be possible; that is, on your turn immediately following a successful Judo parry or grapple. Sacrifice Throw is a special option for All-Out Attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. 365). Use these rules instead of the standard ones for All-Out Attack.

Before you attempt the throw, you must declare whether you intend to land face-up, face-down, or kneeling, as well as where you plan to end up. One of your landing hexes – the only one, in the case of kneeling – must be your hex, your foe’s hex, or a hex adjacent to one of these. You must also state whether you want your victim to end up face-up or face-down, and where, subject to identical restrictions. You can end up in the same place; that is, you can land atop them or pull them down on top of you.

After stating your goal, roll against Sacrifice Throw to hit. Succeed or fail, you immediately end up in your declared posture and location, defenseless due to your All-Out Attack! Your opponent has -1 to dodge or block. They’re at -3 to parry if you fell or at -2 if you only dropped to your knees. If they fail to defend, you throw them exactly as you planned. If you were grappling them, you may let go as a free action, but you don’t have to – it’s common to hang on and follow a Sacrifice Throw with a pin or choke.

This throw is dangerous in combat but common and useful in point-based matches."
	/>
	<element
		name="Scissors Hold"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Wrestling-2."
		prereq="Wrestling; cannot exceed Wrestling skill level."
		desc="This technique allows you to grapple an adversary’s legs using your own. You must have both legs free. You must also be lying face-up, sitting, or standing – but if you’re standing, then successful or not, you automatically end your turn on the ground. Scissors Hold isn’t possible from other postures (kneeling, crouching, etc.).

Roll against Scissors Hold to hit. Your opponent defends normally. If you succeed, you’ve grappled their legs with yours. They may try to break free on their turn. If they fail, or choose not to try, you’ve locked your legs around theirs. They may attempt to break free on subsequent turns, but at a cumulative -1 per turn.

If your foe is standing, Scissors Hold leads naturally to a takedown (GURPS Basic Set, p. 370). Having both of their legs grappled this way gives you +3 in the Quick Contest!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Spinning (Attack)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-2, or -3 for a kick."
		prereq="Karate or any Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This technique involves turning in a circle before attacking. You must specialize. Spinning Punch defaults to Karate-2, and covers all forms of spinning hand and arm strikes. Spinning Kick defaults to Karate-3. Spinning Strike defaults to Melee Weapon-2, and you must specify the skill; e.g., Spinning Strike (Knife). All of these are special options for All-Out Attack or Committed Attack (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 99-100) – use the rules below instead of the normal ones for those maneuvers.

The goal behind spinning before attacking is to deceive your opponent. This might work on a less-skilled adversary, but a skilled fighter is likely to detect your ploy and defend more easily. To simulate this, roll a Quick Contest of Spinning Attack against your opponent’s best melee combat skill before you make your attack roll. If you win, you may subtract your margin of victory from your victim’s defense roll against the blow. If you lose, you 'telegraph' your intentions and your foe may add their margin of victory to their defense! Thus, this move is risky... but it’s still common in tournaments and sport martial arts.

Next, make an attack roll against Spinning Attack. Your target may use any active defense, adjusted by the modifier determined in the Contest. This does add to the penalty for a feint, Deceptive Attack, etc. – a well-executed Spinning Attack can increase the defense penalty while a bad one can cancel it out (or worse). However, if you wish to try a Deceptive Attack, you must apply the penalty for that option to both your roll in the Contest and your attack roll.

As a Committed Attack, a Spinning Attack does normal damage for your punch, kick, or weapon. It leaves you at -3 on all defense rolls and unable to retreat. If you struck with a hand or a weapon, you can’t use it to parry. If you kicked, you can’t dodge at all. These penalties last until your next turn.

As an All-Out Attack, a Spinning Attack involves putting your full weight behind the blow, using an exaggerated spin (360° or more!), and/or making a wide, looping attack. You’re at -2 to skill for both the Contest and your attack roll. However, your damage is at +2 or +1 per die, whichever is better. You have no defenses.

In either case, if you throw a Spinning Kick, balancing during the spin is especially difficult. If your kick misses or your foe successfully defends, the roll to avoid falling is against DX-2.

You can combine Spinning Punch with Elbow Strike (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 71), Exotic Hand Strike (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 71), Hammer Fist (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 73), or Lethal Strike (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 85). Likewise, you can mix Spinning Kick with Lethal Kick (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 85). The GM may permit other techniques, and may allow armed techniques to work with Spinning Strike. See Using Techniques Together (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 64) to find effective skill level."
	/>
	<element
		name="Stamp Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-3 or Karate-3."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This kick consists of a swift, downward stamp with the heel, using your entire body weight to give additional force to the kick. It does more damage than a normal kick, but it can only target an opponent who’s lying down or the foot or leg of a standing foe.

Roll against Stamp Kick to hit. Damage is thrust+1, plus your Brawling or Karate bonus. On a miss, you stomp the ground and must make a DX roll to avoid ending up off-balance and unable to retreat until your next turn."
	/>
	<element
		name="Staying Seated"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Riding."
		prereq="Riding; cannot exceed Riding+4."
		desc="This technique represents special training in the art of staying on the back of a mount. Knights learn it to keep their seat in combat; rodeo riders practice it to win competitions! When rolling for any reason to avoid falling off your mount (for instance, the rolls on GURPS Basic Set p. 397), use Staying Seated instead of Riding."
	/>
	<element
		name="Trip"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Parry-1."
		prereq="Judo, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry."
		desc="Trip lets you cause a two-legged foe to stumble and miss with a slam. It counts as a parry with the prerequisite skill. Success means you avoid the slam and your attacker must make a DX or Acrobatics roll at -5 or fall down!

Per GURPS Basic Set p. 376, a charging fighter’s 'effective weight' as a weapon equals their ST. Since your weight limit with an unarmed parry equals your Basic Lift, Trip fails automatically if your foe’s effective weight exceeds your BL. At ST 8 and BL 13, you couldn’t stop a ST 14+ opponent. With ST 14 and BL 39, only ST 40+ giants would be a problem.

Shield DB doesn’t benefit Trip. You can’t retreat for a bonus, either – or use a Slip or Sideslip (see Retreat Options, GURPS Martial Arts, p. 123-124). You can Dive by assuming a crawling posture across your foe’s path. Apply the usual modifier to your roll and use 2xBL to determine whom you can trip.

You can’t attack with Trip – use Sweep (see above) for that. However, you can use Trip to intercept someone running past you (not merely stepping) within a yard. On a battle map, that’s through your hex or an adjacent hex. This works like a regular Trip and counts as a parry.

Trip can use many body parts: arms, legs, a hip, etc. You must Dive or use a free foot to intercept a runner who isn’t trying to slam you."
	/>
	<element
		name="Two-Handed Punch"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Brawling-2."
		prereq="Brawling; cannot exceed Brawling skill"
		desc="This technique involves either knitting the fingers of two hands together to strike or striking with two fists held together. A common move in movies and on television, it’s not terribly safe or effective in reality.

Roll against Two-Handed Punch to hit. Your opponent defends normally, but if they successfully parry and inflict damage, both of your arms take full damage. If you take damage from striking DR 3+, both hands take full damage. Damage is thrust+1 crushing – or thrust at +1 per die, if better – plus your Brawling bonus.

On a turn when you attempt a Two-Handed Punch, you can only parry once with your hands. This does count as a Cross Parry (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 121) – the parry is more effective but you only get one."
	/>
	<element
		name="Uppercut"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Boxing-1, Brawling-1, or Karate-1."
		prereq="Boxing, Brawling, or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This is a short punch directed upward from a low stance. It delivers a powerful blow to an opponent standing in close. You can only use Uppercut against the upper body – skull, eye, face, neck, torso, arm – of a standing foe. (Exception: If their SM exceeds yours, you can target everything but their feet.) Damage is thrust crushing plus skill bonuses. Your target defends normally.

Uppercut is a very close-range punch. Many fighters throw it after getting their adversary in a clinch with the other arm. Grappling an opponent around the back of their head and punching is illegal in modern sport boxing, but very effective (see Grab and Smash!, GURPS Martial Arts, p. 118)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Wrench (Limb)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="ST-4; cannot exceed ST+3."
		prereq="—"
		desc="This technique involves grabbing and suddenly twisting an enemy’s limb to dislocate or break it. It defaults to ST – not a skill – and must be learned separately for each limb: Wrench Arm, Wrench Leg, and so forth. Wrestling gives its usual skill-based ST bonus.

To use this technique, you must first grapple your opponent by the desired limb using two hands; see Grappling (GURPS Basic Set, p. 370). They may attempt to break free on their turn. If they fail, then on your next turn, roll a Quick Contest: Wrench (Limb) vs. the higher of your victim’s ST or HT. They get +4 if you’re wrenching their leg. This counts as an attack.

If you win, you inflict swing crushing damage on the limb. The target’s rigid DR protects normally. Flexible armor – including natural DR with the Flexible or Tough Skin limitation – has no effect.

Otherwise, you inflict no damage. You may make repeated attempts on later turns. Your opponent may attack you or attempt to break free during this time, subject to the usual limitations of being grappled."
	/>
	<element
		name="Wrench Spine"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="ST-4 or Wrestling-4; cannot exceed ST+3 or Wrestling+3."
		prereq="—"
		desc="Some old wrestling manuals depict techniques for breaking an opponent’s back: pick them up, hoist them over both shoulders, and then pull their leg and arm (or neck) to snap their spine. While not difficult, this procedure is slow and requires great strength. For a rapid, cinematic spine-snapper, see Backbreaker.

Wrench Spine takes several turns to execute. On your first turn, you must grapple your opponent with two hands around the torso. Resolve this as a normal grapple.

If your victim fails to break free on their turn, roll against Wrench Spine on your next turn to hoist them into position. Success means you lift them up and swing them over your shoulders. Any failure means you fall down with your foe on top of you and take thrust damage to your own neck. If your opponent’s weight exceeds your BLx4, you simply can’t pick them up; your attempt fails but you don’t fall or hurt yourself.

On later turns, roll a Quick Contest of Wrench Spine vs. the higher of your victim’s ST+4 or HT+4. If you win, you inflict swing crushing damage. The target is the spine. There’s no wounding multiplier for this location but sufficient injury can mean severe and possibly permanent crippling; see New Hit Locations (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 137). Even if the GM isn’t using the spine hit location in general, they should use those rules for Wrench Spine.

The target’s rigid DR protects normally. Flexible armor, including natural DR with the Flexible or Tough Skin limitation, has no effect. The spine’s own DR doesn’t help, either – you’re not striking the spine but applying continuous pressure to break it.

You may make repeated attempts on later turns. Your opponent may attack you or attempt to break free during this time, subject to the usual limitations of being grappled."
	/>
	<element
		name="Backbreaker"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="ST-3 or Wrestling-3; cannot exceed ST+3 or Wrestling+3."
		prereq="—"
		desc="Some cinematic wrestlers – and strongmen in general – can pick up an opponent and break their spine over their knee. To attempt this, you must first grapple your foe with two hands around the torso. Resolve this as an ordinary grapple.

If your opponent fails to break free on their turn, roll against Backbreaker on your next turn. Success means you lift up your victim, drop to one knee, and smash their back across your other knee. Failure means you drop them; they end up face-up on the ground and you end up kneeling, but neither of you suffers damage. If their weight exceeds your BLx4, you simply aren’t strong enough to pick them up – you waste a turn trying to lift them and can’t proceed with the technique.

A successful Backbreaker does swing crushing damage to the spine. This location has no special wounding multiplier but sufficient injury can do serious harm; see New Hit Locations (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 137). Even if the GM isn’t using the spine hit location, they should use those rules for Backbreaker.

The target’s rigid DR protects normally. Flexible armor, including natural DR with the Flexible or Tough Skin limitation, has no effect. The spine’s DR does apply, as this is a direct blow to the spine."
	/>
	<element
		name="Binding"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill."
		prereq="Judo or Knot-Tying; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		desc="This is the technique of binding a victim limb-by-limb while parrying their attacks. In Japanese legend, guards and police used it to restrain criminals, while ninja used it for abductions. To use Binding, you must have a rope (or hand-cuffs) ready in two hands.

Binding only works in close combat. On your turn after a successful grapple or parry – unarmed or using the rope – you can attempt to bind a limb. To do so, win a Quick Contest of Binding vs. your foe’s DX or best grappling skill. This is an attack. To tie up successive limbs, repeat the process. You can bind two limbs with cuffs, any number with a rope. Your victim can try to free themself on their turn; use the rules for Bolas (GURPS Basic Set, p. 410).

If you bind all of your victim’s legs, they must roll vs. DX-6 every turn or fall down. Their DX and ST are at -6 to resist takedowns and techniques intended to knock them down. If you bind all of their limbs, they’re helpless – although they can attempt an Escape or DX-6 roll to free themself (see Escape, GURPS Basic Set p. B192)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Dual-Weapon Defense"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Block-1 or Parry-1."
		prereq="Any combat skill that gives a Block or Parry score; cannot exceed prerequisite Block or Parry."
		desc="You’re normally at -1 to defend against a Dual-Weapon Attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. 417). This technique lets you buy off that penalty. To ward off both attacks, you must make two defense rolls simultaneously: a parry with either hand or a parry with one hand and a block with the other. Roll against Dual-Weapon Defense for the weapon or shield in each hand.

You can also learn Dual-Weapon Defense for use with a two-yard or longer Polearm, Spear, Staff, or Two-Handed Sword weapon. This lets you buy off the -1 to parry both halves of a Dual-Weapon Attack with a single parry; see Parrying with Two-Handed Weapons (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 123).

A wizard in a cinematic campaign may learn this maneuver with a Blocking spell, to buy off the penalty when defending against two attacks simultaneously; e.g., to cast Ward against an offensive spell at the same time as parrying a sword blow. The wizard must learn the Dual-Weapon Defense technique for the weapon and the spell separately, just as would a warrior defending with two different weapons."
	/>
	<element
		name="Fighting While Seated"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-2."
		prereq="Any combat skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Some cinematic martial artists show their contempt for lesser opponents by remaining seated when attacked. This technique replaces the prerequisite skill while seated; e.g., if you have Karate at 20 and Fighting While Seated (Karate) at 19, you can punch or feint from a seated position at 19, kick at 17, etc. Fighting While Seated also helps with the -2 to defend while seated. If you know it at skill-1, you’re at -1 to defend, while at full skill, you have no penalty.

You may stand on your turn by taking a Change Posture maneuver. To stand instantly, roll against Acrobatic Stand (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 65) at +4. Success lets you take any maneuver normally. Failure means you must take a Change Posture maneuver.

For rules on fighting while sitting on the ground rather than seated in a chair, see Postures, Hit Locations, and Techniques (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 98-99)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Flying Jump Kick" 
		difficulty="Hard" 
		default="Prerequisite skill-7."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill." 
		desc="A 'flying' attack is a devastating blow that gets extra power from a full run and jump at the enemy. Realistic martial artists practice this stunt for show – never for combat. In the movies, though, all bets are off! Flying Jump Kick defaults to Karate-7 and ends in a kick.

This flying attack is a special option for Move and Attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. 365). Use the rules below instead of the normal ones for that maneuver. If you use this technique, it’s all you can do that turn, no matter how fast or skilled you are.

To launch a Flying Jump Kick, you must first make a running broad jump; see Jumping (GURPS Basic Set, p. 352). This requires a DX or Jumping roll. If successful, then at the end of your jump, roll against your level with this technique to hit. 

Your victim parries at -2. If you hit, you inflict your usual damage at +2 – or at +1 per die, if better. Start with kicking damage. 

Afterward, you cannot retreat. Moreover, you cannot dodge. All of your remaining active defenses are at -2. These effects last until your next turn. 

This technique is dangerous! If you fail the roll for your jump or your attack – or if your target successfully defends – you fall unless you can make a DX-8 or Acrobatics-4 roll. On a fall, you suffer damage for a collision with an immovable object (the ground) at an effective Move equal to the full distance of your run and jump."
	/>
	<element 
		name="Flying Lunge" 
		difficulty="Hard" 
		default="Prerequisite skill-4." 
		prereq="Any thrusting Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill." 
		desc="A 'flying' attack is a devastating blow that gets extra power from a full run and jump at the enemy. Realistic martial artists practice this stunt for show – never for combat. In the movies, though, all bets are off! Flying Lunge defaults to Melee Weapon-4 for any thrusting weapon, and involves hurling yourself weapon-first at the foe. 

This flying attack is a special option for Move and Attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. 365). Use the rules below instead of the normal ones for that maneuver. If you use this technique, it’s all you can do that turn, no matter how fast or skilled you are. 

To launch a Flying Lunge, you must first make a running broad jump; see Jumping (GURPS Basic Set, p. 352). This requires a DX or Jumping roll. If successful, then at the end of your jump, roll against your level with this technique to hit. 

Your victim parries at -2. If you hit, you inflict your usual damage at +2 – or at +1 per die, if better. Start with your weapon’s thrusting damage. 

Afterward, you cannot retreat. Moreover, you cannot parry. All of your remaining active defenses are at -2. These effects last until your next turn. 

This technique is dangerous! If you fail the roll for your jump or your attack – or if your target successfully defends – you fall unless you can make a DX-8 or Acrobatics-4 roll. On a fall, you suffer damage for a collision with an immovable object (the ground) at an effective Move equal to the full distance of your run and jump."
	/>
	<element
		name="Grand Disarm"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Fencing weapon skill-9, other Melee Weapon skill-11, or unarmed combat skill-11."
		prereq="Any unarmed combat or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Grand Disarm is a special All-Out Attack that lets you disarm every foe adjacent to you with lightning speed. Use these rules instead of the usual ones for All-Out Attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. B365). If you attempt a Grand Disarm, it’s all you can do that turn, no matter how fast or skilled you are.

A Grand Disarm involves spinning in place – you cannot step – and trying to disarm every single foe within a yard. You must engage your enemies in either clockwise or counterclockwise order (your choice). You can’t combine this with any technique except Disarming (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 70).

Roll against Grand Disarm once per foe, in the order chosen above, to hit their weapon. Your opponents may defend normally. If you critically miss on any of these attacks, your Grand Disarm ends immediately and you must roll on the Critical Miss Table (GURPS Basic Set, p. 556).

After resolving all of the attack and defense rolls, you may try to disarm everyone who didn’t successfully defend! Use the rules on GURPS Basic Set p. 401; you roll against the higher of your weapon skill or your Disarming technique (not Grand Disarm). Resolve each disarming attempt completely before moving to the next. Should you be disarmed during one of these Contests, don’t keep rolling – your turn ends immediately.

Since Grand Disarm is an All-Out Attack, you have no active defenses afterward. In a cinematic game, though, it’s traditional for those disarmed this way to gape and gawk on their next turn – not to attack with another weapon or bare hands. The GM should make an IQ roll for each foe (in over-the-top games, at -1 per successful disarm after the first). Those who fail are mentally stunned (GURPS Basic Set, p. B420) by your awe-inspiring move!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Hand Catch"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Parry-3."
		prereq="Judo, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry."
		desc="This technique – popular with cinematic warriors, muscular henchmen, and super 'bricks' – involves catching an incoming attack in your hand. It isn’t realistic! It’s a one-handed parry, even if the prerequisite skill usually parries with two hands, and incompatible with Cross Parry (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 121).

Roll against Hand Catch to defend, at the usual -2 for Sumo Wrestling vs. a kick, or -3 for Sumo Wrestling or Wrestling vs. a weapon. You cannot retreat. Failure means you’re hit. The attacker may choose to hit their original target, your parrying arm, or your parrying hand. Success means you parry and may roll against the prerequisite skill to grab your attacker, modified as follows.

Modifiers: Against unarmed, -2 to hit a hand or foot; -2 for Sumo Wrestling vs. a foot; -1 if your foe knows Rapid Retraction (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 51). Against armed, a basic -3; another -3 to -5 for weapon size (see GURPS Basic Set p. 400); a further -3 for Sumo Wrestling or Wrestling vs. a weapon.

Success on this skill roll means you grapple the extremity or grab the weapon! On later turns, you can use any combat option or technique that requires a grab or grapple to set up – Disarming, Finger Lock, Judo Throw, Snap Weapon, Wrench Limb, etc., as applicable. Failure means you deflect the attack but fail to catch your attacker.

The GM may let realistic fighters try this technique at default. The consequences of failure are steep enough to keep it under control.

You can also learn Hand Catch for Parry Missile Weapons in order to catch ranged weapons. If you have Precognitive Parry, you can use any Hand Catch specialty for this. Hand Catch can only trap projectiles (not beams) that the underlying parry could deflect. Use the standard modifiers for such parries instead of those above. Success plucks the weapon from the air, regardless of hand DR. Failure means you’re hit. Don’t use Hand Catch to catch something thrown to you – use Catching (GURPS Basic Set, p. B355)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Hand-Clap Parry"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Parry-5."
		prereq="Judo or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry."
		desc="This often-foolhardy cinematic technique – common in samurai stories – lets you trap an opponent’s weapon in mid-stroke. By clapping your hands together, you capture the weapon’s blade, haft, or head.

Roll against Hand-Clap Parry to defend against an attacker’s weapon. Success means you stop the attack and trap the weapon. Failure means you’re hit, and your assailant may choose to hit their original target or either of your hands! Succeed or fail, this is the only parry you may make with your hands this turn.

If you trap the weapon, your enemy’s turn ends immediately. They lose any additional attacks or maneuvers they might have had, and can’t step. They can’t use the trapped weapon to parry or attack until you relinquish it. On future turns, they may try to break free. If they opt to give up their weapon, it’s a free action on their turn.

On your next turn, you may attempt to disarm or use Snap Weapon (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 87). You don’t have to do either – you can act normally while holding onto the weapon, as long as you leave two hands on the weapon and don’t step away from your victim. Relinquishing the weapon is a free action on your turn.

If you make a successful disarm attempt – or your foe releases their weapon – you may try to reverse the weapon and ready it yourself on your next turn. This requires a DX roll. Success means you catch the weapon, which counts as a Ready maneuver. On a critical success, you ready the weapon instantly! Failure means you drop it. On a critical failure, you also inflict Tip Slash (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 13) damage on your torso."
	/>
	<element
		name="Initial Carving"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-4."
		prereq="Any fencing weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="A cinematic swashbuckler can try to carve an initial using their blade. Determine where they’ll carve the initial and the number of strokes they’ll need to carve it – for instance, a Z takes three. The first stroke is at no penalty beyond that for hit location; it’s at -0 on the torso, -5 on the face, and so on. If the stroke inflicts at least a point of cutting damage, it will mark anything but metal or similarly hard materials, ripping cloth (but not armor), scarring skin, and delivering any poison vile enough to need only a scratch. An impaling weapon can make a Tip Slash (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 113) to do cutting damage.

It’s more difficult to align the remaining strokes of the initial relative to the first. The attack roll is at -4 (in addition to hit location modifiers) for an initial roughly 4'x4'. If a subsequent stroke fails by 4 or less, it makes a slash but it isn’t properly connected to the earlier lines – there’s a gap or an overlap (roll a die). This can be bad form; it might even change the initial to another letter! It’s possible to connect lines that are too far apart; try again at the same modifier. The victim might object to the erasing process, however, as this involves at least half a dozen crisscross lines. Initial Carving is generally the realm of the incredibly skilled... or those named Inigo, Ignatz, or Irene.

You must learn a separate technique for each letter. It lets you buy off the -4 for the second and later strokes. To remove the penalties for carving in a specific hit location, buy a Targeted Attack (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 68).

Example: Don Lorenzo Estrada wishes to leave the initials L.E. on the skin of several (unwilling) acquaintances, so they practice long and hard. They spend 4 points on the L and 5 on the E (which takes four strokes, so they want to get it right the first time). Their Rapier skill is 14; they’ll make the first stroke of each letter on a 14 or less. The next part of the L is at default+3, giving a net -1 to skill – they need a 13. The E is at default+4; they have no penalty to carve it at all."
	/>
	<element
		name="Lethal Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Karate-4."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed Karate skill."
		desc="This kick focuses all of your strength onto a toe or toes, converting your blow from crushing to piercing. This lets you target the vitals or eyes. Roll against Lethal Kick to hit, applying the usual hit location penalties. Damage is thrust-1 plus your Karate bonus. Hurting Yourself (GURPS Basic Set, p. B379) applies if your target has any DR – not just DR 3+.

Lethal Kick is generally impossible while wearing fully enclosed shoes or boots, but the GM might allow it with such pointy footwear as cowboy boots and stiletto heels – especially in a cinematic campaign!

As combat options, Lethal Kick and Lethal Strike are reasonable even in a realistic game. The techniques are cinematic because only warriors with Trained by a Master can improve them."
	/>
	<element
		name="Lethal Strike"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Karate-2."
		prereq="Karate; cannot exceed Karate skill."
		desc="This is a hand strike with stiffened fingers. It uses the rules for Lethal Kick, above, but damage is thrust-2 plus your Karate bonus. It’s possible while wearing gloves with individual fingers, even gauntlets, but incompatible with mitts, boxing gloves, etc."
	/>
	<element
		name="Piledriver"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="ST-5 or Wrestling-5."
		prereq="Wrestling; cannot exceed ST or Wrestling."
		desc="Piledriver involves grappling your opponent, turning them upside down, and driving their skull into the ground by sitting down hard. This is a clumsy, risky move, rarely seen outside professional ('entertainment') wrestling. It’s a special All-Out Attack option – use these rules instead of the usual ones for that maneuver.

To execute a Piledriver, you must first grapple your opponent with two hands by the arms, torso, or legs. Resolve this as an ordinary grapple. Your foe may defend normally.

If your enemy fails to break free on their turn, then on your next turn, make a Piledriver roll to turn them head-down and drop to a sitting posture. This counts as an attack. If your victim’s weight exceeds your BLx4, you aren’t strong enough to pick them up – your attack fails automatically but you must still roll to see if you critically fail!

Your victim may defend at the usual penalties for being grappled. If they know the Wrestling skill, they can counter your move by pivoting to make the attack mechanically difficult. This defense counts as a Wrestling parry and is possible even if your foe has no hands free.

A successful Piledriver does thrust+4 crushing or thrust+2 at +2 per die, whichever is greater, plus damage equal to your ST bonus from Wrestling (+1 at DX+1, +2 at DX+2 or better). Apply this to the skull. Immediately afterward, you can attempt a pin as a free action. Your opponent may resist as usual – but they’re still grappled and may be stunned or otherwise suffering from their injuries.

If your Piledriver fails for any reason but being too weak to lift your foe, including a successful enemy defense, you still drop to a sitting posture. You must also roll vs. HT. A failed HT roll means you sit down too hard, strain your gut, etc. Apply the damage you would have inflicted to your own torso. Critical failure on the Piledriver roll means you end up sitting and injure yourself automatically (no HT roll).

A variation is to grapple your adversary, pick them up, and smash their skull-first into the floor, wall, or other fixed object. This is a common tactic for strong men in mixed martial arts bouts – often in response to being grappled. (If you do this without lifting your foe, use Grab and Smash!, GURPS Martial Arts, p. 118, instead.) This move works as described above with three important differences:

	1. If your foe is grappling you with two hands and you have a free hand, you can opt to grapple their head or arm with only one hand as your initial grapple. This is a standard grapple; your rival defends normally. However, if they let go of you on their turn, you can’t attempt a Piledriver on your next turn (you still keep your grapple).
	2. The attack roll is at +3, because you’re not trying to invert your victim after you pick them up.
	3. Damage drops to thrust+2 crushing or thrust at +1 per die, whichever is greater, plus the Wrestling bonus."
	/>
	<element
		name="Pole-Vault Kick"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Karate-4."
		prereq="Jumping and Karate; cannot exceed Karate skill."
		desc="This technique is a variation on Jump Kick (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 75) that uses a pole – typically a quarterstaff but sometimes a sword stuck in the ground or even a convenient banister – to vault into a kick. It involves a short pole-vault forward or side-ways that ends in a sharp kick. It’s a special option for All-Out Attack. Use the following rules instead of the normal ones for that maneuver.

To attempt a Pole-Vault Kick, you must have two hands on a pole, sword, or similar vertical lever. You must take at least two steps toward the foe; this effectively gives you an extra yard of reach. Roll against Pole-Vault Kick to hit. Your target parries at -2.

If you hit, you do thrust+3 crushing damage – or thrust+1 at +1 per die, if better – plus your Karate bonus. If you miss, or if your target successfully defends, you fall down unless you can make a DX-4 or Acrobatics-2 roll. Hit or miss, you have no defense at all until your next turn!

As strange as it may seem, some real-world martial artists do practice this kick, although its effectiveness is doubtful. At the GM’s option, realistic warriors who practice especially flashy styles can buy a Style Perk that lets them improve this technique."
	/>
	<element
		name="Pressure-Point Strike"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite combat skill-2."
		prereq="Either Pressure Points or Pressure Secrets, and a combat skill that’s useful with those skills; cannot exceed combat skill."
		desc="Attacks with the Pressure Points and Pressure Secrets skills are normally at -2 to hit. This technique lets you buy off this penalty."
	/>
	<element
		name="Roll with Blow"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-2."
		prereq="Acrobatics or any unarmed combat skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This represents special training at presenting little resistance to the force of a punch or other bludgeoning attack, resulting in less injury. Whenever you’re hit by a crushing attack, you may roll against Roll with Blow to reduce damage.

Success means you take half damage (round up) before subtracting DR... but double the basic damage roll to calculate knockback (GURPS Basic Set, p. 378). This doubling is cumulative with the effects of attacks that normally cause extra knockback. Make a DX roll at -1 per yard of knockback to avoid falling down. Critical success on Roll with Blow means you take only 1 point of damage (extra knockback still applies).

Failure means you take normal damage and extra knockback. On a critical failure, you also fall down automatically and are physically stunned!

Roll with Blow is risky in places where knockback is likely to mean a collision. In a superhero game, the GM may let anyone learn this skill – people being knocked great distances into and through things is very much in-genre!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Snap Weapon"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="ST-4 or ST-based Jitte/Sai-4; cannot exceed ST+3 or ST-based Jitte/Sai+3."
		prereq="—"
		desc="Cinematic strongmen often use brute strength to snap weapons. You can only attempt this if you trapped the target weapon with a barehanded grab or Bind Weapon (Jitte/Sai) on an earlier turn – or on your turn after making a successful Hand Catch or Hand-Clap Parry. Roll a Quick Contest: Snap Weapon vs. the weapon’s HT. Use HT 10 for missile weapons, HT 12 for melee weapons. Cheap weapons get -2; fine ones, +1; very fine ones, +2. This is an attack. If you win, you inflict thrust crushing damage on the weapon."
	/>
	<element
		name="Springing Attack"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-2."
		prereq="Any unarmed combat or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Springing Attack represents an attack made from the kind of deep stance that some cinematic fighters use to 'store up' energy for a powerful strike. To make an attack like this, you must first crouch. This takes your entire turn – you may do nothing else.

On your next turn, make a roll against Springing Attack – not the prerequisite skill – to hit with your first attack. If you hit, that one attack is at +2 to damage or +1 per die, whichever is better. If you miss, you have -2 to DX and all active defenses until your next turn. On a critical miss, you fall down! If your foe defends, you suffer no special ill effects."
	/>
	<element
		name="Double Eye-Poke"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-5 or Karate-5."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="This is a darting thrust to both eyes using one hand with two extended fingers – often accompanied by suitable sound effects ('Poink!'). The goal isn’t to maim but to distract the victim so you can pull a fast one or run away! If hit, the target must roll vs. HT. Failure means they’re blinded for seconds equal to their margin of failure."
	/>
	<element
		name="Eye-Poke Defense"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill Parry."
		prereq="Any unarmed combat skill; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry+5."
		desc="The best defense against Double Eye-Poke is to place a hand upright along the nose, which forces the attacker’s fingertips to stop short of the eyes. This parry is an ultimate defense, and can go as high as Parry+5. Of course, it only works against Double Eye-Poke..."
	/>
	<element
		name="Flying Atomic Wedgie"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-8 or Wrestling-8."
		prereq="Brawling or Wrestling; cannot exceed pre-requisite skill."
		desc="The Flying Atomic Wedgie is a Move and Attack: you leap past the target, grab hold of their underpants, and pull at full power – hopefully getting the shorts up over their head. If you hit, roll a Quick Contest of ST with the victim. You’re at +1 per yard you ran toward them. If you win, they suffer agony (GURPS Basic Set, p. 428) for minutes equal to your margin of victory and embarrassment for considerably longer."
	/>
	<element
		name="Halitosis Attack"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="HT-5; cannot exceed HT+5."
		prereq="Odious Personal Habit (Foul Breath)."
		desc="This dreaded attack is an attempt to overcome the enemy with bad breath in close combat. To use it, you must grapple your foe from the front or they must do the same to you. On later turns, roll a Quick Contest: your Halitosis Attack vs. your victim’s HT. This counts as an attack.

If you win, you stun your victim for seconds equal to your margin of victory. If you critically succeed or they critically fail, they’re retching for that time instead (GURPS Basic Set, p. 429). If they have No Sense of Smell/Taste, though, they’re immune!

There are persistent rumors of a Flatulence Attack that works on foes who grapple you from behind. The GM should decide whether martial farts suit their campaign."
	/>
	<element
		name="Noogie"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-5 or Karate-5."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="A Noogie is a knuckle rub to the top of the head. If hit, the victim suffers moderate pain on their next turn (only). Repeated hits on successive turns cause this to progress a step a turn to severe pain, terrible pain, and agony. Further attacks extend the agony’s duration. For rules for pain and agony, see GURPS Basic Set p. 428.

The best way to use Noogie is to pin the target and noogie away until they’re in agony. This gives the usual +3 to Intimidation when you finally stop and make demands ('Say ‘uncle’!'). Head DR beyond the standard DR 2 for the skull grants immunity."
	/>
	<element
		name="Nose Slap"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-5 or Wrestling-5."
		prereq="Brawling or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Nose Slap is a close-combat attack that involves grabbing the victim’s nose with one hand and using the other to slap them across the face – all in one smooth motion. If hit, the target is stunned and must roll vs. HT. Failure means they drop anything they’re holding in either hand and clutch their nose. If they have something they can’t drop, like a shield, they hit themself in the face with it. Nyuk!"
	/>
	<element
		name="Wet Willy"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-6 or Karate-6."
		prereq="Brawling or Karate; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="To attempt a Wet Willy, you must first take a Ready maneuver and moisten a finger with saliva. The following turn, roll against Wet Willy to wiggle the slimy finger around in your adversary’s ear. If they’re hit, they must roll as if Squeamish (GURPS Basic Set, p. 156) with a self-control roll equal to their Will. If they’re already Squeamish, they must attempt their normal self-control roll at -3. Failure has the usual effect.
	
You may combine Springing Attack with another striking technique. See Using Techniques Together (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 64) to find effective skill level."
	/>
	<element
		name="Timed Defense"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Active defense-2; cannot exceed active defense."
		prereq="—"
		desc="This technique helps you defend against opponents who use acrobatics or speed to move behind you and attack. It lets you buy off the -2 for a flank or 'runaround' attack (GURPS Basic Set, p. 391) for one active defense. For Block or Parry, you must specialize by combat skill. You may use Timed Defense (Dodge) only once per turn."
	/>
	<element
		name="Badger Game"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Sex Appeal-0 or Intimidation-0. Specialized by primary skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		prereq="Sex Appeal and Intimidation; Acting optional as complementary skill; Fast-Talk required for the 'spouse' role."
		desc="The Badger Game is a classic con in which a romantically appealing supplicant lures the mark into a compromising situation before an apparent spouse or partner arrives to threaten violence, legal action, or embarrassment.

The primary operator (the supplicant) rolls against Sex Appeal to lure the mark, pleading for help and arranging a private meeting. When the mark responds, the 'spouse' enters and makes threats using Intimidation. In most versions of the con, the threat cannot actually be carried out, so the spouse must rely on Fast-Talk instead of true intimidation; this acts as a specious threat (see Manipulation, GURPS Social Engineering, p. 37).

Acting can complement either Sex Appeal or Intimidation. A successful con results in the mark offering a bribe or payoff to avoid exposure. See Blackmail and Espionage (GURPS Social Engineering, p. 49)."
	/>
	<element
		name="Good Samaritan"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Stealth-0 or Acting-0; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		prereq="Stealth and Acting; Stage Combat optional."
		desc="The Good Samaritan con involves two roles: a thief and an apparent rescuer. The thief sneaks up on the victim and takes a wallet or purse using a Quick Contest of DX or ST – Pickpocket skill is deliberately not used, since the thief is supposed to be noticed!

The thief then runs, allowing the 'rescuer' to chase them out of sight. Moments later, the rescuer returns with the wallet and makes an Acting roll. On a success, the victim presses a reward onto the 'reluctant' rescuer; on success by 5 or more, the victim may provide an even greater reward (often a check exceeding the cash found in the wallet).

Stage Combat can assist the performance of the chase and struggle but is not required."
	/>
	<element
		name="Shell Game"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Fast-Talk-0; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4. Specialized by skill."
		prereq="Fast-Talk; Sleight of Hand; shills require Acting."
		desc="The Shell Game technique represents the ability to run the classic three-shell con or its card-based variant (Find the Lady/Three-Card Monte). The operator entices the mark into betting on which shell hides the pea after a rapid shuffle. In practice, the operator palms the pea using Sleight of Hand so that no shell contains it.

Sleight of Hand is not part of the deceptive technique itself but is a required prerequisite and may be improved as a separate Hard technique. Shills assist the con with Acting; when dealing with a reluctant mark, a shill may 'bet' and 'win' with an Acting+5 roll, providing a complementary bonus to the operator’s Fast-Talk.

The technique covers misdirection, patter, timing, and stagecraft involved in running the game convincingly."
	/>
	<element
		name="Spanish Prisoner"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Acting-0; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		prereq="Acting; Fast-Talk optional but useful."
		desc="The Spanish Prisoner is a long-form con carried out by a single operator, who claims to act on behalf of an imprisoned nobleman possessing a vast fortune inaccessible until release. Freeing him supposedly requires ransom money, bribes, or other expenses – but the nobleman promises a generous reward.

The con relies heavily on secrecy and emotional manipulation, often embellished with the claim of a grateful and beautiful daughter when targeting a romantic mark. Acting is used to maintain the narrative, justify increasing 'expenses', and keep the victim invested as new 'difficulties' arise.

The modern evolution of this con is the Nigerian 419 fraud, involving deposed foreign officials, frozen bank accounts, and requests for electronic funds transfer codes. The technique covers the performance, scripting, and psychological pressure required to maintain the illusion until the mark catches on or is fully defrauded."
	/>
<element
	name="Agenda"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Diplomacy."
	prereq="Diplomacy; cannot exceed Diplomacy+3."
	desc="You are skilled at simplifying a complex request for aid or information by breaking it down into action items (in Latin, agenda) or bullet points. This offsets the penalty to an Influence roll for a complex request. Roll against Agenda as modified by the penalty for complexity, or the basic Diplomacy skill, whichever is less. You can’t gain a net bonus from applying this technique to an inherently simple request!"
/>
<element
	name="Big Store"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Leadership."
	prereq="Leadership; cannot exceed Leadership+5."
	desc="This is less a con in its own right than an enabler or enhancer for other cons. It has many variants, but all involve setting up what looks like an ongoing organization, but is really a false front with nothing behind it – and therefore costs far less.

The Big Store is a group performance effort with a formal leader, who makes the Big Store roll (see Team Efforts in GURPS Social Engineering, p. 33-34). This complements a roll vs. the average Acting skill of the group’s members. If the members are all NPCs, the GM may assign them a rating of Novice (effective skill 10), Trained (effective skill 12), Good (effective skill 14), or Elite (effective skill 16). Unfamiliarity or other penalties may apply:
• -2 to both the Big Store and Acting rolls if the leader and group haven’t worked together for at least two weeks.
• -2 to both the Big Store and Acting rolls if the mimicked organization is a type the leader and group haven’t rehearsed together at least eight times.
• -2 to the Big Store roll if the physical setting is a quick improvisation (creating an elaborate “stage set” avoids this penalty; higher-budget setups can give bonuses as for high-quality equipment).

A Big Store can act as an enhancer to many sorts of long cons, and even some kinds of short cons. When it’s used that way, treat the group’s Acting as a complementary skill to the main roll for bringing off the con. However, having multiple “performers” doubles the modifiers: -4 for critical failure, -2 for failure, +2 for success, +4 for critical success. Some long cons require a Big Store setup to make them possible at all. Roll a Quick Contest of the group Acting skill (aided by the Big Store roll) vs. the mark’s IQ. If it works, the mark accepts the setup as a bookmaking operation, charity, church or temple, stock brokerage, or whatever sort of organization it pretends to be, and the con can proceed. A comparable, though less elaborate, setup is needed for some short cons, such as fortune-telling fraud (where the “fortune teller” offers to remove a curse from the mark’s money)."
/>
<element
	name="Close Dancing"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Dancing."
	prereq="Dancing; cannot exceed Dancing+5."
	desc="In couples dancing, where you have the same partner for an entire dance, you can use Close Dancing in an Influence roll toward a partner who is capable of being romantically interested in you. This may represent any level of contact from the touching of hands to a full-body embrace; the effect comes from being a little closer than is culturally accepted."
/>
<element
	name="Dangerous Request"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Savoir-Faire (High Society)-3."
	prereq="Savoir-Faire (High Society); cannot exceed Savoir-Faire (High Society)."
	desc="Ordinarily, requests for aid or information have a -3 modifier if helping or answering would endanger the subject. If you have invested in Dangerous Request, you can reduce or negate this modifier by suggesting that your higher standing makes it more dangerous to refuse to help you."
/>
<element
	name="Elevated Speech"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Savoir-Faire (High Society)."
	prereq="Savoir-Faire (High Society); cannot exceed Savoir-Faire (High Society)+5."
	desc="You have mastered a variety of formulae for honoring and expressing good will toward a social elite. You can use Elevated Speech in Influence rolls for standard requests made in public, such as gaining admission to a royal court."
/>
<element
	name="Elicitation"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Prerequisite skill."
	prereq="Any Influence skill except Intimidation; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+5."
	desc="This technique provides a subtler method for getting information than Interrogation. In fact, ideally, the subject doesn’t realize he was being questioned, or doesn’t know what the topic was! Basically, Elicitation is a request for information, handled not as a reaction roll but as an Influence roll. The questioner approaches the topic indirectly, while overtly seeming to converse about something else; apply a penalty of the questioner’s choice to the Influence skill, and the same penalty to the subject’s Will. If you have bought up Elicitation, roll against either Elicitation with the penalty applied, or the unmodified Influence skill, whichever is less; that is, Elicitation lets you steer the conversation in a less obvious way, but is never more effective than just coming out and asking."
/>
<element
	name="Mission Assignment"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Leadership-5."
	prereq="Leadership; cannot exceed Leadership."
	desc="Roll against Mission Assignment when you are sending NPC members of a combat team into danger, but not going yourself (see GURPS Basic Set, p. 204). On a success, they carry out your orders as if you were there."
/>
<element
	name="Pig in a Poke"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Fast-Talk."
	prereq="Fast-Talk; cannot exceed Fast-Talk+5."
	desc="One of the oldest con games, going back to the Middle Ages. It involves selling a “pig” concealed in a bag for a customer to butcher. Roll a Quick Contest of Fast-Talk vs. IQ; if you win, the victim is distracted from actually looking in the bag. The animal in the bag, though alive and squirming and about the size of a piglet, turns out to be a cat or a small dog. The Gold Brick is another version of this scam. The White Van Scam (selling supposedly hot, bootlegged, or off-the-books goods, often electronic, that turn out to be defective or worthless) combines Pig in a Poke with Big Store (for the van, uniforms, and packaging; see Pyramid 3/54: Social Engineering, p. 4-5)."
/>
<element
	name="Piggybacking"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Intelligence Analysis-5."
	prereq="Intelligence Analysis; cannot exceed Intelligence Analysis."
	desc="The big challenge in memetics is getting a newly introduced meme past the resistance of the target population (treated as a Quick Contest of Propaganda vs. average Will). Piggybacking bypasses this resistance by attaching the new meme to one that is already current in the target population. Treat the margin of success on the Piggybacking roll as a penalty to the effective Will of the target population."
/>
<element
	name="Short Change"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Fast-Talk."
	prereq="Fast-Talk and Sleight of Hand; cannot exceed Fast-Talk+5."
	desc="Short-change artists have tricks for getting more money back from a store clerk or bank teller than they handed over, by engaging in multiple exchanges involving stacks of small bills, which overload the victim’s mind so that he loses track of the correct totals. Roll a Quick Contest of Short Change vs. IQ; your margin of victory acts as a penalty to the victim’s Per or Observation roll to resist your Sleight of Hand. Some short-change artists have an accomplice ask the victim for service immediately afterward, delaying his realization that he has a problem."
/>
<element
	name="Truce"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Savoir-Faire (Military)."
	prereq="Savoir-Faire (Military); cannot exceed Savoir-Faire (Military)+4."
	desc="When a military force (of at least five people) under your command is in a potential combat situation with another military force, you may attempt Truce rather than relying on a reaction roll. Roll a Quick Contest of Truce vs. Will. If you win, the other side has a Good reaction. If you tie or lose, roll their reaction normally. Modifiers: +2 if you succeed at a Leadership roll first, as it makes your force look more prepared for battle. If you are leading a force larger than what your Military Rank justifies, a penalty equal to the difference between your Rank and that normally required for command."
/>
<element
	name="Beguilement"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Prerequisite skill-5."
	prereq="Voice and any of Diplomacy, Fast-Talk, Performance, Politics, Public Speaking, Sex Appeal, or Singing; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="You have learned to pitch your voice to appeal to a hearer’s emotions. Roll a Quick Contest of Beguilement vs. Will after you have spoken for a minute. If you succeed, the hearer’s Will is reduced by your margin of victory for any Influence rolls you attempt in the next hour. You can have this effect on an entire crowd or a single person, but if you apply it to an entire crowd, you gain the benefit only when you try to influence the entire crowd."
/>
<element
	name="Crowd Song"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Musical Influence."
	prereq="Musical Influence and Singing-12; cannot exceed Musical Influence+5."
	desc="As seen in many musical comedies, when you start singing, you can inspire your listeners to form a chorus, singing and (optionally) dancing. Apply your margin of success as a bonus to their Singing and Dancing skill; if they don’t have these skills, start at their default values. A member of the audience who doesn’t want to take part can resist with Will, but he’ll stand out dramatically if he succeeds, and will feel the urge to make his exit. If the entire audience is hostile, they can all try to resist with a single roll vs. average Will."
/>
<element
	name="Fascination"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Sex Appeal-5."
	prereq="Charisma 1 and Sex Appeal; cannot exceed Sex Appeal."
	desc="Fascination is achieved by gazing steadily into the eyes of a potential lover. It does not work on anyone who could not be sexually attracted to you, or who cannot see you. It’s normally done at close range; apply a penalty of -1 per full yard of separation. After five minutes, roll a Quick Contest of Fascination vs. the target’s Will; your Charisma adds to this roll. The effects are somewhat like those of Hypnotism. Your target is not put to sleep, but will passively gaze into your eyes as long as you hold his gaze, and he will respond to your suggestions as if he had made an Excellent reaction roll. You cannot give him “posthypnotic suggestions.” He has a penalty equal to your margin of victory in the Quick Contest to notice ordinary interruptions. He has no penalty to notice threats to his life or his highest values. If he does notice any interruptions, the fascination is broken."
/>
<element
	name="Personal Guarantee"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Diplomacy-2."
	prereq="Charisma 1 and Diplomacy; cannot exceed Diplomacy."
	desc="In attempting to establish a relationship of personal trust (see Building Trust in GURPS Social Engineering, p. 40), you can make an immediate offer, rather than waiting a month to gain trust. Buying up this technique reduces the penalty for such immediate offers. If the offer is accepted, it represents trust in your visible personal integrity. This technique only applies with an initial offer; if that’s not accepted, you still need to wait a month before the next offer to avoid a -2 penalty."
/>
<element
	name="Power Gaze"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Intimidation-5."
	prereq="Charisma 1 and Intimidation; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="This is the direct gaze of a king or other superior, which in legend lesser mortals cannot meet. Roll a Quick Contest of Power Gaze vs. Will at the first meeting of eyes. If you win, the other person must lower his eyes, and for the duration of the encounter, his Will is at a penalty against your Influence rolls equal to your margin of victory. If you succeed by 5 or more points, he must make an immediate Fright Check, at a penalty equal to your Charisma. This effect requires a meeting of eyes at close range; apply a -1 penalty per full yard of distance."
/>
<element
	name="Resonance"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Prerequisite skill-5."
	prereq="Voice and one of Performance, Public Speaking, or Singing; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="When you recite a poem (with Performance or Public Speaking) or sing a song (with Singing), the quality of your voice helps make it stick in people’s minds. Roll a Quick Contest of Resonance vs. the average Will of the audience. Any audience member who tries to recall the poem or song afterward gets your margin of victory as a bonus to IQ for a roll to remember the words and melody. If this doesn’t work on the first such try, the person has forgotten the song. He may get another attempt, if he attends another performance and if the bonus from that performance is higher than the previous bonus."
/>
<element
	name="Anachronistic Training"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Special (see below)."
	prereq="Any one TL skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="This technique allows you to use the prerequisite skill without suffering a TL penalty for antique or anachronistic methods. Each level of this technique removes one level of TL penalty; a TL8 Patrolman with Anachronistic Training (Artillery)-2 would take no TL penalties for Artillery/TL7 or /TL6 rolls, and would make Artillery/TL5 rolls at the -1 penalty for skills one TL lower. Anachronistic Training cannot be used to remove the penalty for futuristic gear or methods. The GM may still enforce a familiarity penalty for unfamiliar equipment. You must buy this technique for each skill separately."
/>
<element
	name="Historical Familiarity"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="prerequisite skill-4."
	prereq="Archaeology, Egyptology, or History; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="Your intensive training in ancient societies gives you some familiarity with the overall geography and cultural norms (such as manner of dress and certain styles) of a certain period of time. You may default to the relevant Area Knowledge (or, at the GM’s discretion, Current Affairs) from Archaeology, Egyptology, or History instead of IQ, and gradually buy off the -4 default. Each historical specialty is a separate technique."
/>
<element
	name="Armed Grab"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill -2."
	prereq="any grappling skill or appropriate Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="To grab an opponent at Reach C with a weapon, roll against Armed Grab, based on the appropriate weapon skill. For Reach C sticks or flexible weapons, you may base it on your grappling skill. With a flexible weapon, you must grab with at least two hands; you can Transition to a one-handed armed grapple afterward. See Entangle (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 71) for an alternative."
/>
<element
	name="Attack from Nowhere"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill-3."
	prereq="Extradimensionality and any unarmed or Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="You slip into the fourth dimension to await and ambush a foe. Preparing this requires a Quick Contest: your Stealth vs. his Vision (usually at -6 for Extradimensionality’s fringe effect). Roll against Attack from Nowhere to strike into three-dimensional space. If you won the Quick Contest, your target has no active defense; otherwise, he defends at -2. If you have 4D Spatial Sense, its bonus cancels the default penalty and you needn’t buy this technique. If you have Hypervision, you can retreat further into hyperspace, so that you’re completely invisible and your victim automatically has no active defense. If your opponent has Hypervision, he contests your Stealth with unmodified Vision regardless of how far you’ve moved into hyperspace."
/>
<element
	name="Disorient"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Judo-3."
	prereq="Extradimensionality and Judo; cannot exceed Judo."
	desc="On your turn after a successful Judo parry, you may use Disorient to attack the opponent you parried. He may attempt any active defense – but if he fails, you throw him through the fourth dimension to any location within 10 yards of you! He must roll vs. Body Sense (defaults to Acrobatics-3 or DX-6). Failure means he’s disoriented and can do nothing but defend for one turn. Critical failure causes him to fall down, physically stunned; his recovery rolls are against DX. If this is his first experience of hyperspace, failure at Body Sense also triggers a Fright Check, at -5 for critical failure."
/>
<element
	name="Local Orientation"
	difficulty="Hard"
	defaults="Acrobatics or Dancing."
	prereq="Extradimensionality, Body Sense, and Acrobatics or Dancing."
	desc="An advanced variation on Facing Change: You use your control of spatial dimensions to change your personal “up” and “down” in a gravity field. Apply -3 to Local Orientation for a barely perceptible tilt (others roll vs. Perception or Observation to notice, at +2 for 3D or 4D Spatial Sense), -5 for a different direction (standing on walls), or -8 for reversal (standing on the ceiling). Then roll against the lower of your modified technique or unmodified skill to execute the stunt. Making such a shift gives you an extra +2 when retreating. You can use this to “fall upward,” but you take normal falling damage (GURPS Basic Set, p. 430-432) upon landing!"
/>
<element
	name="Phantom Attack"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill-4."
	prereq="Extradimensionality and Boxing, Karate, or a fencing skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="By attacking through four-dimensional space, you can strike past three-dimensional physical armor, gaining an armor divisor of (5). Your unarmed attacks can target the vitals at the usual -3 without being impaling or piercing. If you target the skull (-7), your armor divisor does affect skull DR."
/>
<element
	name="Bonesetting"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Varies."
	prereq="Surgery."
	desc="Setting bones isn’t necessarily invasive, but as it involves manual manipulation, and trauma surgeons are trained to do it, it’s part of Surgery. A simple fracture (lasting crippling; see GURPS Basic Set, p. 422) requires a Surgery roll, plus or minus the ST difference between surgeon and patient. Bonesetting is possible without instruments, so many of the TL penalties for surgery don’t apply. The technique buys off the -1 for working without X-rays and -2 for working without anesthesia. Compound fractures (permanent crippling) are beyond the limits of low-tech medicine. This technique cannot exceed Surgery unless explicitly permitted."
/>
<element
	name="Trepanning"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Varies. Cannot exceed Surgery+4."
	prereq="Surgery."
	desc="Making a hole in the skull by removing a circular piece of bone, by scraping, cutting away the rim, or drilling (see Trephin, GURPS Low-Tech, p. 148). Practiced since the Paleolithic, this procedure can relieve pressure on the brain after a crushing blow to the skull (treat as stabilizing a mortal wound, GURPS Basic Set, p. 424) or, at the GM’s option, relieve Chronic Pain (GURPS Basic Set, p. 126) due to migraines."
/>
<element
	name="Cataract Surgery"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Varies."
	prereq="Surgery."
	desc="Using a needle to pierce the eyeball and treat cataracts (see Eye Surgery Instruments, GURPS Low-Tech, p. 149). This can reduce Bad Sight to normal vision or Blindness to Bad Sight, if the problem is due to cataracts. The technique buys off the -2 for eye surgery and -5 for non-field-expedient low-tech surgery for this operation. When learning this technique, base Surgery on DX (not IQ). This technique cannot exceed Surgery unless explicitly permitted."
/>
<element
	name="Cutting for the Stone"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Varies."
	prereq="Surgery."
	desc="Making an incision into the bladder to extract a bladder stone. This counts as minor surgery (see Surgery and Surgical Equipment, GURPS Low-Tech, p. 147). This technique buys off the -5 for non-field-expedient low-tech surgery for this operation. This technique cannot exceed Surgery unless explicitly permitted."
/>
<element
	name="Thong Throwing"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Thrown Weapon (Spear)-2."
	prereq="Thrown Weapon (Spear); cannot exceed Thrown Weapon (Spear)."
	desc="This technique uses a thong wrapped around a javelin. When releasing the weapon, the thrower pulls back on the thong, imparting spin. This improves Acc and Range (see Muscle-Powered Ranged Weapon Table, GURPS Low-Tech, p. 77).

Readying a javelin for such a throw requires two hands and a Ready maneuver."
/>
<element
	name="Bow &amp; Palette Firestarting"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Survival."
	prereq="Survival or having seen the skill practiced before; cannot exceed Survival+4."
	desc="This is the technique of starting a fire using a wooden palette and a rod. The rod is placed in a small insertion in the palette and spun rapidly, either by hand or by using a simple bow. Flammable material is also placed in the hole, and the friction of the spinning rod will ignite it. This will take 1 to 5 minutes. In the World of Banded Night setting (GURPS Lands Out of Time, p. 38), the societies of Cavemen, Advanced Saurians, and Tarn have learned how to use this technique. Primitive Cavemen, Neanderthals, Primitive Saurians, and Protohumans have not developed this technique, though individual Primitive Cavemen and Neanderthals may have learned it from other cultures.

Modifiers: +3 if two people work together; -5 if the packing is wet; -3 if the palette and spindle are wet; -1 if the palette is damp."
/>
<element
	name="Flint Sparking"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Survival+1."
	prereq="Survival or having seen the skill practiced before; cannot exceed Survival+5."
	desc="This is the technique of starting a fire by striking sparks with two rocks. One must contain bits of flint or iron; the second must be non-porous. Banging the stones together creates sparks which can ignite dried tinder. This process is time-consuming and can take minutes or hours. Roll 4d6 to determine how many minutes pass before a skill check can be made. Characters with a relative skill level of +3 roll 3d6, those with a relative skill level of +4 or more roll 2d6. In the World of Banded Night setting (GURPS Lands Out of Time, p. 38), the societies of Cavemen, Primitive Cavemen, Advanced Saurians, and Tarn have learned how to use this technique. The Neanderthals, Primitive Saurians, and Protohumans have not developed this technique.

Modifiers: +3 if two people work together; -5 if the kindling is wet; -3 if the kindling is damp."
/>
<element
	name="Cane Travel"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="DX-6."
	prereq="None."
	desc="Primarily, those who are blind use this technique, but it can also be applied in lightless environments, such as many caves. Feeling your way with a cane or staff can detect hazards without walking into them (see Perception, GURPS Underground Adventures, p. 10). Cane Travel can offset much of the penalty for movement in total darkness. Its use substitutes for taking extra time (GURPS Basic Set, p. 346); the combination of Cane Travel with extra time cannot allow a better roll than DX-1 to move without vision.

Alternatively, Cane Travel may default to Blind Fighting-5, with a maximum of Blind Fighting, if the GM allows this skill."
/>
<element
	name="Bracing"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Masonry-3."
	prereq="Masonry; cannot exceed Masonry."
	desc="Bracing is the technique of setting up props to hold up the ceiling of a tunnel or to support the construction of an arch. This task normally suffers a -3 penalty for specialists who haven’t trained it, but Bracing buys off that penalty. At the GM’s discretion, Masonry rolls for Bracing may receive modifiers depending on tunnel quality, available materials, or architectural stability."
/>
<element
	name="Hoisting"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Masonry-3."
	prereq="Masonry; cannot exceed Masonry."
	desc="Hoisting is the technique of building a crane or lifting structure to raise a massive load. This task normally takes a -3 penalty when performed without specialization. Hoisting buys off that penalty. At the GM’s discretion, Hoisting may default to Seamanship-3 instead, and Seamanship may replace Masonry as its prerequisite, representing sailors trained in rigging and lifting gear."
/>
<element
	name="Scaffolding"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Masonry-3."
	prereq="Masonry; cannot exceed Masonry."
	desc="Scaffolding is the technique of building a framework for masons or miners working above the ground or above the floor of a mine. The task normally carries a -3 penalty without specialized training. Scaffolding buys off that penalty. The GM may apply modifiers based on the height involved, materials used, and the stability of the surrounding structure."
/>
<element
	name="Penetration Diving"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Scuba-2."
	prereq="Scuba; cannot exceed Scuba."
	desc="This is a technically specialized form of diving, practiced when direct ascent to breathable air is impossible, as in cave diving (GURPS Underground Adventures, p. 12) or exploring wrecks or submerged structures. Preparations include carrying extra air for emergencies, multiple light sources, and guidelines to help you navigate. If you roll above your Penetration Diving, but not above your Scuba skill, you get lost and must roll vs. Navigation (Underground) (GURPS Underground Adventures, p. 21) to find your way out before your air runs out."
/>
<element
	name="Total Exhalation"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Escape+1."
	prereq="Escape; cannot exceed Escape+3."
	desc="This is exhaling as completely as possible before squeezing through a tight passage. It raises the caver’s chances of getting through, but at a risk: A critical failure means being stuck. See Narrow Passages (GURPS Underground Adventures, p. 12) for the effects. A successful roll against Breath Control gives +1 to Total Exhalation, or +2 on a critical success. This can exceed Escape+3."
/>
<element
	name="Branch Fingers"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Wooden Arm-2."
	prereq="Wooden Arm (GURPS Magic Plant Spells, p. 21); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="Your fingers extend into twisted, thin branches. This increases your effective SM by 1 for the purpose of calculating Reach (GURPS Basic Set, p. 402), but the DR granted by the spell is halved (to DR 2) and your hand and arm can be crippled with the normal amount of injury. As a side effect, your punch is more of a “poke,” doing piercing damage instead of crushing. This adds 2 energy to the casting cost."
/>
<element
	name="Contagious Creeping Moss"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Gather Moss-4."
	prereq="Gather Moss (GURPS Magic Plant Spells, p. 13-14) and Pestilence; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="Anyone who touches the subject of your Gather Moss spell must make a HT roll. If he fails, he is infected by the spell and suffers right along with the subject. If his roll succeeds, he is immune for five seconds. This adds 4 energy to the casting cost."
/>
<element
	name="Create Book"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Create Paper-4."
	prereq="Create Paper (GURPS Magic Plant Spells, p. 12); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="You can bind the created paper into a book. The binding is no different from any typical book at the caster’s TL. This adds 2 energy to the casting cost for a cheap, flimsy binding and cover; 4 energy for a soft-but-sturdy binding and cover; or 6 energy for a high-quality binding and hard cover."
/>
<element
	name="Seaweed Clutch"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Capturing Vines-4."
	prereq="Capturing Vines (GURPS Magic Plant Spells, p. 12); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="Animates a mass of seaweed instead of normal vines. You’ll need a minimum of one hex of seaweed per victim. It has no DR. Victims in water risk drowning. This adds 4 energy to the casting cost."
/>
<element
	name="Targeted Creeping Moss"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Gather Moss-4."
	prereq="Gather Moss (GURPS Magic Plant Spells, p. 13-14); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="Using this technique, you can begin the spread of the moss at any location you touch. If, for example, you touch the subject’s neck when you make the spell roll, moss appears on his neck first. It then spreads to the other locations, in the established order. This adds 4 energy to the casting cost."
/>
<element
	name="Bullet Parry"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Parry Missile Weapons Parry-5."
	prereq="Parry Missile Weapons and Enhanced Time Sense; cannot exceed Parry Missile Weapons Parry."
	desc="This is the technique for bouncing bullets off a melee weapon – or your arms, if you have suitable bracers, wristbands, or gauntlets, or just high DR. It lets you buy off the penalty for parrying bullets by intense mental focus on maintaining high speed.

At a further -4 penalty, you can catch bullets rather than simply parrying them. You can’t offset this penalty with the Bullet Parry technique, but you can with Speed Talent or Time Mastery Talent (see GURPS Supers, p. 122).
Enhanced Time Sense doesn’t normally allow parries against light-speed weapons such as lasers – but the GM may allow this, still at -5, if the defender also has Precognition (GURPS Basic Set, p. 77). Parrying energy beams is a different Hard technique. See Bulletproof (GURPS Supers, p. 122) for more on this topic."
/>
<element
	name="Camouflaged Mind Block"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Mind Block-4."
	prereq="Mind Block; cannot exceed Mind Block skill."
	desc="Mind Block provides non-psis with a defense against having their minds read – but it’s obvious that you’re using it, from the repetitive patterns of standard mind blocks. This technique uses a pattern of stream-of-consciousness prose crafted to sound like your natural thoughts.

If you win the standard Quick Contest of skills, not only are your real thoughts not apparent, but it’s not obvious that you’re hiding something.

The pattern you use repeats after a minute or two; under prolonged telepathic examination, roll at -1 per extra minute after the first – but if the Quick Contest fails by that modifier, all that’s revealed is that you have a mind block in place; your true thoughts are still hidden."
/>
<element
	name="Coded Thoughts"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Mind Block-6."
	prereq="Mind Block and Cryptography; cannot exceed Mind Block skill."
	desc="A variant of Mind Block, which lets you translate your thoughts or knowledge into a different symbolism. For example, you might turn a message into a string of numbers or even a melody.

This may not disguise the fact that you’re hiding something, because your code appears to be a standard mind block, but instead of hiding the secret behind the barrier, it makes it part of the barrier.

If a telepath penetrates the Mind Block, the actual secret won’t be the first thing to come into your thoughts. He has to probe one layer deeper, or memorize the coded form of your thoughts and crack it."
/>
<element
	name="Human Missile"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Acrobatics-3, Aerobatics-3, Aquabatics-3, or Jumping-3."
	prereq="Acrobatics or Jumping and the Super Jump advantage; Aerobatics and the Flight advantage; or Aquabatics and one of Amphibious, Aquatic, Enhanced Move (Water), or Flight (if usable underwater). Cannot exceed base skill."
	desc="This is a variant of a slam attack. You can fling yourself at a target, such as a vehicle or building, with your whole body tense and acting as a single rigid mass, and with your striking surface minimized. Typically this means having your clenched fists raised above your head, striking the target first like a spear point.

Targets must be larger than you (SM at least 1 higher than yours). Your damage is huge piercing instead of crushing. You can target vital areas or small windows.

When you hit the target, you naturally tend to smash into or through it rather than knocking it back, so you can treat the target as an immovable object (see GURPS Basic Set, p. 431)."
/>
<element
	name="Multiport"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Body Sense."
	prereq="Body Sense and the Warp advantage with Rapid Fire; effective level cannot exceed Body Sense."
	desc="This technique is used in combat teleportation with the Rapid-Fire enhancement (see Combat Teleportation, GURPS Supers, p. 126) in place of Body Sense skill.

It cannot give a net bonus to Body Sense skill; if your effective level with Multiport after the penalties for Rapid-Fire Teleport (see GURPS Supers, p. 29) is higher than your Body Sense, reduce it to Body Sense before applying other penalties."
/>
<element
	name="No-Mind"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Mind Block-5."
	prereq="Invisibility Art and Mind Block; cannot exceed Invisibility Art skill."
	desc="An advanced development of Mind Block skill, No-Mind works like Invisibility Art, but against telepathic powers rather than sight."
/>
<element
	name="Remote Hypnosis (Supers)"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Hypnotism."
	prereq="Hypnotism; Telepathy Talent 1, or any other talent relevant to influencing others’ minds; special limits."
	desc="In a campaign setting where hypnotism is based on “animal magnetism” or some other mysterious force, hypnotists can influence their subjects at a distance, without words or gestures, and even through physical barriers such as walls. The same is true for any hypnotist who has Telesend.

Putting the subject into a trance to begin with requires face-to-face contact; but once subverted you can transmit new suggestions directly from mind to mind, at a modifier based on distance taken from the Speed/Range Table on GURPS Basic Set, p. 550.

If you buy levels of this technique, you can use them to offset distance penalties up to a maximum of Hypnotism-1.

You don’t necessarily know what suggestions are appropriate unless you have a Mindlink or other telepathic connection, or some form of technological remote sensing.

If you have the Telesend advantage, you can do the same thing at +2 to Hypnotism skill (see GURPS Basic Set, p. 201) using the long-distance range penalties; this technique doesn’t offset those penalties, and there is little point in learning it. It’s for hypnotists whose telepathic powers are purely a product of their skill."
/>
<element
	name="Tight Beam"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Innate Attack (Beam)-2."
	prereq="Innate Attack (Beam); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="You can narrow your beam attack to impact a smaller cross-section of the target. This turns crushing attacks into piercing attacks and non-tight-beam burning attacks into tight-beam burning attacks (see GURPS Basic Set, p. 399). It has no effect on other types of beam attacks.

You can target your foe’s eyes or vitals, or small glass windows or other vulnerable areas on a vehicle.

To train in this technique, you must take Perk: Unusual Training."
/>
<element
	name="Burst-Fire"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Guns-2."
	prereq="Guns; cannot exceed Guns."
	desc="This technique enables you to buy off the -2 to Guns when firing full-automatic, regardless of burst length. Burst-fire is relatively easy to master, but lack of training results in poor performance. This also covers issues like avoiding overheating."
/>
<element
	name="Payload Warhead"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Guns-2."
	prereq="Guns; cannot exceed Guns."
	desc="This technique enables you to buy off the -2 to Guns when firing payload warheads from shotguns, flare pistols, grenade launchers, gyrocs, etc., that perform differently than ordinary single or multiple projectiles, such as HE, illumination, smoke, tangler, tear gas, thermobaric, etc. The technique accounts for minimum and maximum distances, fuse lengths, estimating flight for different warhead weights, etc."
/>
<element
	name="Chariot Archery"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Bow-6."
	prereq="Bow; cannot exceed Bow skill."
	desc="This technique lets you use a bow effectively while riding in a chariot or other wheeled vehicle. The modifiers for firing while moving (GURPS Basic Set, p. 397) can never reduce your Bow skill below your Chariot Archery level. (Other penalties apply normally.) For instance, if you had Bow-13 and Chariot Archery-11, the penalties for archery from a moving vehicle would never reduce your skill below 11, before other modifiers."
/>
<element
	name="Hang From Saddle"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Riding-3."
	prereq="Riding; cannot exceed Riding-1."
	desc="This is the trick riding feat of hanging sideways from one side of a mount, so that most of the body is not exposed to fire from the other side (GURPS Basic Set, p. 397). This is always slightly more difficult than riding while upright and facing forward."
/>
<element
	name="No-Hands Riding"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Riding-3."
	prereq="Riding; cannot exceed Riding skill level."
	desc="This skill controls a horse or other suitable mount without reins, bridle, or bit, communicating with it through posture shifts and knee pressure. It substitutes for Riding skill for this type of riding."
/>
<element
	name="Purse Cutting"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Knife-5."
	prereq="Knife."
	desc="Learned by thieves, this technique involves grasping a purse or other small item in one hand and cutting through its strings or cord with the other. If successfully executed, it leaves the purse in the thief’s possession. The GM makes a Per roll for the victim. If the Purse Cutting roll’s margin of success is greater than that for the Per roll, the victim remains unaware of the theft."
/>
<element
	name="Sharp Turn"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Teamster-1."
	prereq="Teamster; cannot exceed Teamster skill level."
	desc="Charioteers use this technique to avoid the penalty for 120º turns. At top speed, a chariot has a turning radius of 2 yards; that is, a charioteer can execute a 60º turn after moving 2 yards. A sharp turn increases this to a 120º turn (or a 60º turn after a yard). Making a sharp turn requires a roll vs. Teamster-1 (see Pushing the Envelope, GURPS Basic Set, p. 395). After learning this technique, a charioteer can make such turns without penalty."
/>
<element
	name="Shoot Backward"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Bow-4."
	prereq="Riding and Bow; cannot exceed Bow skill level."
	desc="This skill allows shooting at a target to the rear while twisting in the saddle of a mount. It does not aid in controlling the mount; roll vs. Riding-1 for that."
/>
<element
	name="Shoot Over Mount"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Bow-4."
	prereq="Riding and Bow; cannot exceed Bow skill level."
	desc="This skill allows shooting over (or under) a mount while bending or hanging over one side, to hit a foe on the far side. It does not aid in controlling the mount; roll vs. Riding-3 or Hang From Saddle (above) for that."
/>
<element
	name="Behind-the-Back Shot"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Guns-7."
	prereq="Guns; cannot exceed Guns-4."
	desc="This technique lets you shoot under your armpit, over your shoulder, or between your legs to peg a foe behind you without firing wildly or changing facing. The arm(s) used to control the weapon must be free to move in order to position the gun, and you have to be aware that your target is there in the first place! One method works as follows: pull your weak arm tightly against your chest to get it out of the way. Place the dominant hand with the gun under your shoulder pointing backward, slightly canted away from your body to ensure reliable functioning and case ejection. Turn the head as far to the weak-hand side as possible to get a glimpse of your opponent.

Roll against Behind-the-Back Shot to hit. This is a standard ranged attack, at an extra -1 if you target a specific hit location. You’re at -2 to all active defenses until your next turn.

Note that in a realistic setting, you can only improve the technique to Guns-4, unlike the cinematic version (Gun Fu, GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 25)."
/>
<element
	name="Close-Hip Shooting"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Guns."
	prereq="Guns; cannot exceed Guns+3."
	desc="“Hip shooting” refers to shooting done without raising the gun high enough to use its sights (GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 11-13). A special application of hip shooting is to engage an adversary at arm’s reach – that is, in close combat, where a gun normally gives a penalty equal to its Bulk (GURPS Basic Set, p. 391). The Close-Hip Shooting technique represents training for this contingency: the shooter holds his weapon close and fires instinctively. In close combat, apply the Bulk penalty to your Close-Hip Shooting level, then use the lower of your modified technique or your unmodified shooting skill to figure your attack."
/>
<element
	name="Close-Quarters Battle"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Guns."
	prereq="Guns; cannot exceed Guns+4."
	desc="You’ve practiced shooting on the run at nearby targets – a situation known to tactical shooters as “close-quarters battle” (CQB). Whenever you take a Move and Attack maneuver (GURPS Basic Set, p. 365) to fire at a target whose distance from you in yards doesn’t exceed your Per plus Acute Vision (if any), apply the penalty for shooting on the move (-2 or firearm’s Bulk, whichever is worse) to your Close-Quarters Battle level. Then use the lower of your modified technique or unmodified shooting skill to figure your attack."
/>
<element
	name="Combat Driving"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Relevant vehicle-operation skill."
	prereq="Relevant vehicle-operation skill; cannot exceed Riding+4."
	desc="This technique represents training at driving under combat conditions. Use it instead of the relevant vehicle-operation skill whenever you roll to control your vehicle in battle. It doesn’t cover fighting, but where the rules limit weapon skill to the relevant vehicle-operation skill, your limit is Combat Driving instead."
/>
<element
	name="Combat Piloting"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Relevant vehicle-operation skill."
	prereq="Relevant vehicle-operation skill; cannot exceed Riding+4."
	desc="This technique represents training at piloting under combat conditions. Use it instead of the relevant vehicle-operation skill whenever you roll to control your vehicle in battle. It doesn’t cover fighting, but where the rules limit weapon skill to the relevant vehicle-operation skill, your limit is Combat Piloting instead."
/>
<element
	name="Double-Loading"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Fast-Draw (Ammo)-2."
	prereq="Fast-Draw (Ammo); cannot exceed Fast-Draw (Ammo) skill."
	desc="You’ve practiced simultaneously reloading two chambers of a multi-barreled gun or a revolver, or inserting two shells into the tube magazine of a shotgun. A successful Double-Loading roll gives all the benefits of Fast-Draw (GURPS High-Tech, p. 42) and means that each Ready maneuver taken to insert or manually extract one cartridge affects two cartridges. This shaves off one extra second per pair of cartridges if the firearm ejects all of its casings at once, or two extra seconds per pair if the weapon requires you to extract each empty by hand."
/>
<element
	name="Dual-Weapon Attack (Guns)"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill-4."
	prereq="Any shooting skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="If you attack with two guns at once, you’re normally at -4 on each attack unless you have Extra Attack. This technique lets you buy off that penalty. To remove the extra -4 for the “off” hand, you’ll also need either Ambidexterity (GURPS Basic Set, p. 39) or Off-Hand Weapon Training (GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 39).

DWA is primarily for Guns (Pistol), but can be learned for any shooting skill. The only absolute requirement is that you can use two weapons at once. DWA is seldom learned by realistic shooters (see Akimbo Shooting, GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 32).

You must learn DWA separately for each skill.

Per GURPS Basic Set, p. 417, when both attacks target the same foe, he defends at -1. Against guns, this only affects parries like attempts to slap the gun away in close combat (GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 25-26). Dodge is unaffected."
/>
<element
	name="Fanning"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Guns (Pistol)-4."
	prereq="Guns (Pistol); cannot exceed Guns (Pistol) skill."
	desc="This technique lets you buy off the basic -4 to Guns (Pistol) for fanning a single-action revolver with RoF 1 held in one hand. See Fanning (GURPS High-Tech, p. 14). Historically, Fanning wasn’t common with real gunfighters, but popular with trick shooters."
/>
<element
	name="Fast-Firing"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Guns-4."
	prereq="Guns; cannot exceed Guns."
	desc="This technique lets you buy off the first -4 to skill for fast-firing a weapon with RoF 2 or 3. See Fast-Firing (GURPS High-Tech, p. 14)."
/>
<element
	name="Immediate Action"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="prerequisite skill-4."
	prereq="Armoury or any shooting skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="This technique permits you to buy off the basic -4 to clear a stoppage. See Immediate Action (GURPS High-Tech, p. 17). When learning Immediate Action, base shooting skill on IQ, not on DX. Shooting skill versions default to the Armoury specialty used with the relevant weapons, also at -4, but you must still choose a shooting skill specialty, not an Armoury one."
/>
<element
	name="Masked Shooting"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="prerequisite skill-4."
	prereq="Any shooting skill; cannot exceed Guns (Pistol) skill-1 or any other prerequisite skill-2."
	desc="You can reduce the basic -4 to shoot a weapon while wearing a diving mask, gas mask, etc. See Sighted Shooting (GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 13). Long arms specialties like Rifle, Shotgun, and SMG can’t be improved to better than Guns-2 since such masks prevent proper cheek weld."
/>
<element
	name="Precision Aiming"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Guns-6."
	prereq="Guns and Observation; cannot exceed Guns."
	desc="This technique enables you to buy off the –6 to Guns when rolling to claim extra Aim bonuses. See Precision Aiming (GURPS High-Tech, p. 26-27). Rifle is by far the most common specialty! When learning this technique, base shooting skill on IQ, not on DX."
/>
<element
	name="Quick-Shot"
	difficulty="Average"
	default="Guns-6."
	prereq="Guns; cannot exceed Guns."
	desc="This technique lets you buy off the –6 to use a RoF 2+ gun to shoot two targets in one second. See Shooting at Several Opponents (GURPS High-Tech, p. 17-18)."
/>
<element
	name="Retain Weapon (Guns)"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="DX."
	prereq="None."
	desc="You must specialize by Guns specialty. When wielding a suitable weapon, you may use Retain Weapon instead of DX whenever somebody actively tries to disarm you (GURPS Basic Set, p. 401). Should an adversary try to disarm you using brute strength, you may make a ST-based Retain Weapon roll instead of a ST roll; find your ST-based level by subtracting DX and adding ST. This is commonly trained by modern law-enforcement officers."
/>
<element
	name="Targeted Attack (TA)"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="see below."
	prereq="Guns, Gunner, or Liquid Projector; special maximum."
	desc="Hits on “high-value” targets – face, chinks in armor, weapons, etc. – are effective fight-stoppers. Policemen often aim for the legs and special-ops soldiers for the brain (see The Mozambique Drill, GURPS High-Tech, p. 15-16).

For each Targeted Attack (TA), the gunman must specify a shooting skill and a target. The target can be any hit location other than the torso (Eye, Face, Arm, etc.), chinks in armor at a specific hit location (e.g., Torso Chinks), or Weapon. The shooting skill must be capable of attacking that target – usually relevant for attacks against vitals or skull (GURPS Basic Set, p. 399-400).

Default penalty: equal to the modifier to hit the target:
–2: Arm, Leg
–3: Groin, Pelvis, Vitals
–4: Hand, Foot
–5: Face, Neck
–7: Skull
–9: Eye

For chinks in armor: –10 for any location (replaces that location’s penalty), except –8 for torso chinks.

Weapon: assume –4; roll at +1 vs. large weapons (rifle, etc.), –1 vs. small ones (dagger, holdout pistol, etc.).

By improving TA, the shooter can buy off up to half of the default penalty (round up). Write the technique as “TA (Specialty/Target)”.

Examples:
TA (Pistol/Leg) defaults to Guns (Pistol)-2 and can’t exceed Guns-1.
TA (SMG/Skull) defaults to Guns (SMG)-7 and can’t exceed Guns-3."
/>
<element
	name="Thumbing"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Guns (Pistol)-2."
	prereq="Guns (Pistol); cannot exceed Guns (Pistol) skill."
	desc="This technique allows you to buy off the –2 to Guns (Pistol) for thumbing a revolver. See Thumbing (GURPS High-Tech, p. 14)."
/>
<element
	name="Two-Handed Thumbing"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Guns (Pistol)-2."
	prereq="Guns (Pistol); cannot exceed Guns (Pistol) skill."
	desc="This technique permits you to buy off the –2 to Guns (Pistol) for thumbing a single-action revolver held in two hands. See Two-Handed Thumbing (GURPS High-Tech, p. 14)."
/>
<element
	name="Work by Touch (Guns)"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Armoury-5."
	prereq="Armoury (Small Arms); cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="Changing a barrel, clearing a major malfunction, and many other non-combat Armoury applications are at –5 if you must work by touch – e.g., in the dark or while wearing night-vision goggles (GURPS Tactical Shooting, p. 19-20). With sufficient practice, it becomes second nature."
/>
<element
	name="Bite"
	difficulty="Average"
	defaults="DX or Brawling."
	prereq="None."
	desc="The basic bite attack. Note that you must be in close combat to bite. Brawling adds damage as normal.

† With the Biting Mastery perk, use Karate for the default, maximum, and damage bonus."
/>
<element
	name="Rake"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Ground Fighting (Brawling or Karate)-3."
	prereq="Brawling or Karate, and the Claws advantage; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="This technique requires that both the attacker and target are prone, face-up, or crawling, and that the attacker has grappled the target. Some creatures set up this attack for the following turn by taking All-Out Attack (Double) to perform a flying tackle, pounce, or slam followed by a grappling attempt. Note that creatures with unusual postures or numbers of limbs may not need to meet these conditions; in these cases, the GM may wish to modify the technique as required.

Rake is a form of All-Out Attack (Double), and replaces the rules for that maneuver. The aggressor holds his enemy with both hands, tucks his legs up between them, and tears downward with both feet, ripping into his target’s abdomen or thighs with his claws.

Roll to attack twice, once for each foot. Each successful attack inflicts thrust+2 crushing damage, plus the Brawling or Karate bonus. Claws on the feet add any damage bonus, and may change this damage from crushing.
The attacker must choose between targeting the torso with both attacks, or the legs with one attack each. The legs may be targeted without the usual -2."
/>
<element
	name="Scratch"
	difficulty="Hard"
	defaults="Brawling-2 or Karate-2."
	prereq="Brawling or Karate, and the Claws advantage; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="This is a claw attack intended to tear the skin, causing shallow wounds that bleed profusely. Roll damage normally as for a hand attack. If any damage at all penetrates armor and natural DR, the target takes 1 point of injury only, but rolls for bleeding (GURPS Basic Set, p. 420) at -1 per scratch sustained.

At the GM’s discretion, this can have additional effects. For example, a scratch attack to the face (at a further -5) sends blood into the target’s eyes, causing Vision penalties of -3 or more, while inflicting scratches all over the target’s body for several turns may force a Fright Check."
/>
<element
	name="Underwater Combat"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill."
	prereq="Any Melee Weapon skill."
	desc="Attacks made with melee weapons underwater normally suffer a penalty of -4 per yard of maximum reach, even if used to attack at closer range (GURPS Martial Arts: Yrth Fighting Styles, p. 22). Someone trained in underwater combat may apply the penalty to his level in this technique instead of to the prerequisite skill. However, final effective skill with this technique cannot exceed base skill minus half the underwater penalty.

Example: An adventurer with Spear-15 and Underwater Combat (Spear)-21 wields a long spear: Reach 2, 3, for -12 underwater. His effective skill is 21-12 = 9. This is also equal to 15 (base skill) - 6 (half the underwater penalty).

If he later picks up a shorter spear – Reach 1, 2, for just -8 underwater – his skill doesn’t rise to 21-8 = 13, because it is capped at 15 (base skill) - 4 (half the underwater penalty) = 11.

Underwater versions of other techniques may default from the Underwater Combat technique. The default is based on the fighter’s effective skill, as calculated above.

For instance, if the person in the example invested 3 points in Targeted Attack (Underwater Spear Thrust/Vitals), altering the penalty for a vitals strike from -3 to -1, his effective skill when thrusting for the vitals with the Reach 1, 2 spear would be 10 (the capped underwater skill of 11, minus 1 for the Targeted Attack).

Both the underwater skill cap and the Targeted Attack cap apply.

A cinematic underwater warrior with the Terrain Adaptation (Underwater) advantage (GURPS Martial Arts: Yrth Fighting Styles, p. 24) has no need for this technique."
/>
<element
        name="Coordinated Attack"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="prerequisite skill."
        prereq="Any combat skill."
        desc="Fighters who practice together may learn this technique for use when coordinating with members of that group only. It has no maximum level.

Apply Coordinated Attack modifiers to this technique and use the result instead of combat skill for the attack. If it exceeds combat skill, reduce it to that level before applying other modifiers."
/>
<element
        name="Cutting Out"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="prerequisite skill-4."
        prereq="Any Per-based social interaction skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
        desc="Normally, all the members of a small cohesive group will react to you as indicated by a single reaction roll or Influence roll (see Approachability, GURPS Social Engineering, p. 25). This technique lets you spot one member of the group who is susceptible to being approached as an individual.

You receive +1 to his reaction roll (+3 on a critical success); the reaction roll for the rest is unaffected. If you prefer, you may apply the bonus to an Influence roll against your specific target."
/>
<element
        name="Going Viral"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Propaganda."
        prereq="Propaganda and Psychology (Applied); cannot exceed Propaganda+3."
        desc="Viral marketing (GURPS Social Engineering, p. 62) involves crafting a message that makes members of the audience want to repeat it or pass it along. The bonus from improving this technique replaces the bonus from spending more on a campaign, without requiring a higher budget; you cannot claim both benefits."
/>
<element
        name="Hinting"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="prerequisite skill."
        prereq="Any Influence skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+6."
        desc="Hinting makes you skilled at influencing others without being obvious to bystanders. Each Influence skill has its own associated Hinting technique.

You may use your technique to offset skill penalties from subtlety (GURPS Social Engineering, p. 36), while still suffering Perception and Observation penalties normally.

Apply all penalties for subtlety to this technique, then roll against the lower of:
• your modified technique, or
• your unmodified Influence skill.

Thus, bonuses from Hinting can only offset subtlety penalties, never give a net bonus."
/>
<element
        name="Irony"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="prerequisite skill."
        prereq="Public Speaking or Writing; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+5."
        desc="You are skilled at negative arguments that undermine an opponent’s position (see Dialectic, GURPS Social Engineering, p. 35), giving a bonus to the audience’s effective Will to resist adopting his point of view.

This technique lets you offset the penalties to your own effective skill that result from using irony, increasing your ability to make your points indirectly.

Apply all penalties for irony to this technique, then roll against the lower of:
• your modified technique, or
• your unmodified presentation skill.

Thus, bonuses from Irony can only offset irony penalties, never give a net bonus."
/>
<element
        name="Sociometry"
        difficulty="Average"
        default="Sociology."
        prereq="Sociology and Mathematics (Statistics); cannot exceed Sociology+5."
        desc="You have mastered mathematical techniques for analyzing social networks and identifying key members within them. You can spot nonobvious relationships in a social situation (Relationships, GURPS Social Engineering, p. 26), social arbiters of exclusive communities (Inner Circles, GURPS Social Engineering, p. 59), or alpha users for viral marketing campaigns (GURPS Social Engineering, p. 62)."
/>
<element
        name="Dream Rehearsal"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Dreaming."
        prereq="Dreaming; cannot exceed Dreaming+5."
        desc="Consciously reliving successful default skill use in dreams can help you acquire the skill. Roll vs. Dream Rehearsal, halve your margin of success, and round up to find your bonus to IQ rolls for points-based learning (GURPS Social Engineering: Back to School, p. 5-7). Any success gives a minimum of +1; critical success always gives at least +5."
/>
<element
        name="Memory Palace"
        difficulty="Average"
        default="IQ-5; cannot exceed IQ."
        prereq="None."
        desc="As described by Roman orators, who called this the method of loci, you visualize a building, including its furnishings and rooms. To retain information (e.g., the key points of a speech), link each fact to an object that you place somewhere in the building. For example, if the murder weapon was a knife, visualize a bloody knife on the kitchen table.

You can roll against Memory Palace to recall specific facts (roll at IQ-5 if you have no training). Each point invested in the technique gives +1 to IQ rolls for Points-Based Learning (GURPS Social Engineering: Back to School, p. 5-7) and to the number of points you can spend on Heroic Learning (GURPS Social Engineering: Back to School, p. 19-20). Putting five points into Memory Palace means you’ve acquired Eidetic Memory! If you already have Eidetic Memory, learning Memory Palace is of no benefit – it doesn’t help you advance toward Photographic Memory, even if that’s learnable in your campaign."
/>
<element
        name="Versification"
        difficulty="Average"
        default="Poetry."
        prereq="Poetry; cannot exceed Poetry+4."
        desc="You can put information in poetic form to aid in remembering it. Your verses aren’t literary art, but they’re understandable and catchy. For anything you’ve versified, you can recall specific details by making an IQ roll, as with Eidetic Memory. If Eidetic Memory would give you +5, you gain +1 to IQ per two points of success at a Versification roll, rounded up. Any success gives +1, and a critical success always gives at least +5."
/>
<element
        name="Eavesdropping"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Possession-4."
        prereq="Possession; cannot exceed Possession-3."
        desc="You can perceive the surface thoughts of your opponent as though you were using Mind Reading (GURPS Basic Set, p. 69) against him. You must take a Concentrate maneuver, spend 3 MCP, and win a Quick Contest of IQ vs. the higher of your opponent’s Trained Will or Mind Block. Win or lose, the effects are identical to those of Mind Reading."
/>
<element
        name="Enervation"
        difficulty="Average"
        default="Possession-3."
        prereq="Possession; cannot exceed Possession technique."
        desc="You must already be engaged in a possession to use this technique. Roll against Enervation to hit; your opponent defends normally. If you hit, you must spend MCP to set the upper boundary for fatigue, but Mental Control Points spent on Enervation count double for this purpose. After spending MCP, roll a Quick Contest of your Trained Will against the better of your opponent’s Trained HT or Trained Will. If you win, you inflict the lesser of your margin of success or twice the MCP spent as fatigue damage."
/>
<element
        name="Feint (Possession)"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Exorcism, Meditation-2, Mental Strength, Possession, or Trained Will."
        prereq="Possession; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
        desc="Feints represent lulls in the mental assault to draw a host into false confidence, mixing up types of attacks or tactics, etc. This technique replaces any attack or defense skill for the purpose of making or resisting feints. Beats (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 100-101) based on ST don’t make sense, but ruses (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 101) are certainly fitting."
/>
<element
        name="Inquisition"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Eavesdropping-2."
        prereq="Eavesdropping; cannot exceed Eavesdropping technique."
        desc="You can dig into your opponent’s mind and root out specific knowledge he possesses as though you are using Mind Probe (GURPS Basic Set, p. 69). You must take a Concentrate maneuver, spend 3 MCP, and win a Quick Contest of IQ or Interrogation vs. the higher of his Trained Will or Mind Block. Win or lose, the effects are identical to those of Mind Probe."
/>
<element
        name="Mental Contact"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Possession-4."
        prereq="Possession; cannot exceed Possession technique."
        desc="You may take a Concentrate maneuver, spend 3 MCP, and roll against Mental Contact to convey a short message directly to your host’s mind. This is completely nonvocal and cannot be heard by anyone else. The message may be spoken words, images, emotions, etc., but they do not hamper the host in any way – they merely communicate information."
/>
<element
        name="Possession"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="IQ-6 or Will."
        prereq="Cannot exceed controlling attribute/characteristic."
        desc="This technique allows you to buy off the -6 penalty to IQ when making possession attacks."
/>
<element
        name="Stagger"
        difficulty="Average"
        default="Possession."
        prereq="Possession; cannot exceed Possession technique."
        desc="Often employed to create an opening, this technique allows you to stun your opponent. You must be engaged in a possession attempt and win a Quick Contest of Stagger vs. the highest of your opponent’s Trained Will, IQ, or Mental Strength. If you win, your opponent must roll against IQ. On a failure, he’s mentally stunned. This is an attack."
/>
<element
        name="Steal Possession"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Possession-4."
        prereq="Possession; cannot exceed Possession technique."
        desc="Make a possession attack against someone else’s host normally. If you succeed in inflicting MCP, reduce the possessor’s hold on the host by the amount rolled, and increase your own grip by as much."
/>
<element
        name="Terrorize"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Mental Contact-4."
        prereq="Mental Contact; cannot exceed Mental Contact technique."
        desc="You can truly terrify your potential host. Take a Concentrate maneuver, spend 3 MCP, and roll a Quick Contest of Trained Will. You may substitute Intimidation or Kiai, and your opponent may substitute Mental Strength. If you win, your opponent rolls 3d plus your margin of victory and looks up the effect on the Fright Check Table (GURPS Basic Set, p. 360)."
/>
<element
        name="Exercises"
        difficulty="Average"
        default="Teaching."
        prereq="Teaching and a combat or athletic skill; cannot exceed Teaching+3."
        desc="Creates a series of movements – such as a drill or a kata – suited for practicing the basics of a skill. Useful for the first two points in a skill, but not for higher levels. In addition to improving Teaching skill for the purpose of instructing a class or preparing instructional materials, each point in the technique gives +1 to students’ monthly study rolls (GURPS Social Engineering: Back to School, p. 5).

At the GM’s option, Exercises may be applied to performing-arts skills, intellectual skills, or even some social skills such as Savoir-Faire (High Society, Military, or Servant)."
/>
<element
        name="Legendary Teaching"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Teaching-5."
        prereq="Teaching and a relevant special advantage."
        desc="You’re one of those rare teachers who train true heroes in their skills, as the centaur Chiron trained Achilles, Heracles, and Theseus. Whether through inspiration, divine wisdom, or advanced scientific methods, you can pass on knowledge extraordinarily quickly, teach cinematic skills and techniques, and even impart mastery comparable to your own. Legendary Teaching is the basis of Heroic Learning (GURPS Social Engineering: Back to School, p. 19-20); the rules for it appear there.

The archetypal “relevant special advantage” for this technique is Trained by a Master, but similar combat-related advantages (Gunslinger, Heroic Archer, Weapon Master, etc.) are no less fitting. Other spheres call for different advantages: Charisma 3+ for Influence and social skills; Gadgeteer for technological skills; Harmony with the Tao (GURPS Thaumatology: Chinese Elemental Powers, p. 15) for peaceful cinematic skills; Magery 3+ for spells and magical skills; and three levels of a power Talent for powers.

At the GM’s discretion, three levels of a skill-related Talent may grant access to this technique, as an alternative benefit that replaces the reaction bonus (see GURPS Power-Ups 3: Talents, p. 18-19). Enlightened Teacher (GURPS Social Engineering: Back to School, p. 20) lets you teach any skill you know in this way!"
/>
<element
        name="Grabbing Parry (Alternate)"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="prerequisite skill Parry-2."
        prereq="Judo, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry-1."
        desc="While in close combat, you can grab an attacking limb with a Grabbing Parry. With an extra -1, you may grab the attacking hand or foot instead. Grabbing Parry is one-handed or one-armed; if you use Cross Parry (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 121), which gives +1 to your defense, you may grab with both hands/arms.

If the attacker has the Rapid Retraction perk, your margin of victory must be at least 2 for you to successfully grab. This replaces the rules for Judo Parry setups and realistic uses of Hand Catch."
/>
<element
        name="Grabbing Parry"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="prerequisite skill Parry-2."
        prereq="Judo, Sumo Wrestling, Wrestling, or appropriate Melee Weapon skill; cannot exceed prerequisite Parry."
        desc="This technique replaces Hand Catch.

When attacked with a strike or an attempt to grapple a new location, you may try to grab your foe during the parry! You may not use Grabbing Parry if your foe is attacking to improve an existing grapple.
Choose a legal parry and defense option (if desired); you can capture a striking arm (or weapon!), grab a kick, slip in and grapple the torso (see Retreat Options, GURPS Martial Arts, p. 123), etc. Success grapples your foe with the limbs used, but inflicts CP based on 0.5 × ST regardless.

You may capture the leg or the foot at Reach C, or just the foot at Reach 1 – but to follow up with grappling techniques, you must enter close combat.

Parrying a swung weapon with Grabbing Parry can be very dangerous. Unless the fighter can step into close combat and parry the attacker’s limbs, apply Harsh Realism for Unarmed Fighters (GURPS Martial Arts, p. 124) to inflict half damage to all parrying limbs even on a successful parry (one arm for Judo, two arms for Sumo Wrestling or Wrestling); reduce damage by 1 for every point by which the parry is made.

Modifiers:
Against unarmed:
• -1 to grapple an armored leg, -2 for a hand or foot;
• -1 per level of foe’s Rapid Retraction (Pyramid 3/34: Alternate GURPS, p. 30).

Against armed:
• -3 if using Judo or parrying a thrust with Sumo Wrestling or Wrestling,
• -6 if parrying a swing with Sumo Wrestling or Wrestling;
• an extra -3, -4, or -5 if the goal is to bypass a Reach C, 1, or 2+ weapon, respectively, to grab the arm or hand holding it."
/>
<element
        name="Power Techniques"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Controlling attribute at the penalty assigned by the relevant advantage."
        prereq="Possession of an advantage that assigns a specific penalty to a particular use; cannot exceed controlling attribute or the associated power skill."
        desc="Power Techniques allow characters to “buy off” the penalties that certain advantages impose on specific special actions. Each such specialized feat becomes a Hard technique that defaults to the controlling attribute at the penalty listed in the description of the advantage. The technique may be improved normally, but cannot exceed the controlling attribute. If the campaign uses power skills, then Power Techniques default to the appropriate power skill at the same penalty, and their maximum level is capped by that skill.

At the GM’s discretion, characters without full powers may still learn individual Power Techniques if they possess a suitable ability that justifies the feat, but only characters with true powers may benefit from power Talent or power skills when improving these techniques.

Example: Healing is at -6 to repair a crippled limb. The GM may allow a healer to learn Repair Limb as a Hard technique. It defaults to IQ-6 and cannot exceed IQ (or default+6). In a game using power skills, it would default to Healing-6 and could not exceed the Healing skill."
/>
<element
        name="Running the Pole"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Acrobatics-2."
        prereq="Acrobatics; cannot exceed Acrobatics."
        desc="Roll against Running the Pole each turn to avoid falling! Attacks and defenses suffer the usual penalties for bad footing. The default of -2 assumes smooth, level ground. On rough or uneven ground, apply another -2 that can’t be bought off. The Chariot Training perk in GURPS Low-Tech halves this extra -2 and eliminates bad-footing penalties."
/>
<element
        name="Setup Attack"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="prerequisite skill-6."
        prereq="Any unarmed or Melee Combat skill; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
        desc="A setup attack is used to impose a defensive penalty on a fighter’s next attack, as long as that attack is launched on his current or immediately following turn. A successful setup attack is a real attack, and if it succeeds, it strikes home as usual. In addition, a successful attack imposes -2 to Parry, as well as -1 to Block and Dodge. Turning Setup Attack into a technique makes it viable for explicit inclusion into Combinations (see GURPS Martial Arts, p. 80)."
/>
<element
        name="Sight-Reading"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Musical Instrument-2 or Singing-2."
        prereq="Musical Instrument or Singing, and cannot have Can’t Read Music; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
        desc="In societies that have musical notation, playing a new piece from written music gives -2 for unfamiliarity. A musician who improves Sight-Reading can roll against it instead to play any unfamiliar piece straight from the written music."
/>
<element
        name="Trading in Illegal Goods"
        difficulty="Hard"
        default="Merchant-3."
        prereq="Merchant; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
        desc="Merchants who lack Streetwise at 12 or more and don’t specialize in illegal goods are at -3 when dealing with these. However, a relatively unconnected fence (Streetwise 11 or less) – even if he’s an amateur – can still learn the basics about these dangerous ventures."
/>
<element
	name="Debugging"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill-3."
	prereq="Any skill useful for operating a newly invented device; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
	desc="When testing a new invention, roll once weekly vs. the relevant version of Debugging to find bugs (see GURPS Basic Set, p. 474, 476). Identifying the appropriate skill may take some creativity! For example, plausible operating skills for Ontogenetics (GURPS Powers: The Weird, p. 11-12) are Animal Handling and Teaching."
/>
<element
	name="Facing Change"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Body Sense or Acrobatics-3."
	prereq="Acrobatics or Body Sense; cannot exceed Body Sense+5 or Acrobatics+2."
	desc="During movement into or out of hyperspace, you can alter your body’s orientation as a free action and without disorientation. Roll at -2 if you change facing or at -5 if you go from horizontal to vertical or vice versa. Your effective skill after the penalty cannot exceed Body Sense or Acrobatics-3."
/>
<element
	name="Heuristics"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Philosophy-6."
	prereq="Illuminated and Philosophy; cannot exceed Philosophy skill."
	desc="Heuristics is the art of discovering the truth, guided by philosophical insight into the nature of reality. A successful Heuristics roll grants +2 to any skill used to discover an unknown truth or reach a moral decision. Critical success gives +4. Failure produces no insight; critical failure sets you on the wrong track, so that only critical success on the primary skill can point you to the truth."
/>
<element
	name="Illumination"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Teaching-6."
	prereq="Illuminated and Teaching; cannot exceed Teaching skill."
	desc="You have special methods of instruction suited to passing on the Illuminated state (GURPS Basic Set, p. 60). These are based largely on asking questions the student must reflect on at length between face-to-face sessions. Treat this as intensive training (GURPS Basic Set, p. 293), but dependent on Will rather than HT."
/>
<element
	name="Inspired Development"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill."
	prereq="Gadgeteer and any skill useful with it; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
	desc="You’re cinematically gifted at turning sketchy plans into working models. You must specialize in a skill useful for inventing. When making a Prototype roll using that skill, apply all relevant modifiers to your Inspired Development level. Then use the lower of your modified technique or unmodified inventing skill for your Prototype roll."
/>
<element
	name="Inspired Research"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill."
	prereq="Gadgeteer and any skill useful with it; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
	desc="You’re cinematically gifted at dreaming up radical new inventions. You must specialize in a skill useful for inventing. When making a Concept roll using that skill, apply all relevant modifiers to your Inspired Research level. Then use the lower of your modified technique or unmodified inventing skill for your Concept roll."
/>
<element
	name="Mind Modification (Trait)"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="prerequisite skill."
	prereq="Brainwashing, Hypnotism, Propaganda, Psychology, or Teaching; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+6."
	desc="Used to remove or add one specific mental or behavioral trait with a particular skill. Apply -1 to your Mind Modification level per full 5 points of the trait removed or added. Then use the lower of your modified technique or unmodified skill for the roll. Base time required is eight hours; multiple sessions grant a bonus for extra time (GURPS Basic Set, p. 346). Using Telesend in this process gives +2."
/>
<element
	name="Projection"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Meditation-6."
	prereq="Intuitive Mathematician, Mathematics (Pure), Meditation, and Style Familiarity (Tesseraxis); cannot exceed Meditation skill."
	desc="A roll vs. Projection allows you to visualize and enter four-dimensional space; see Tesseraxis (GURPS Powers: The Weird, p. 13). If you concentrate for one minute (the shortest possible time), your Projection roll is at -5; taking extra time (GURPS Basic Set, p. 346) gives bonuses that can compensate for this. You have an additional penalty equal to twice your encumbrance level (e.g., Heavy encumbrance gives -6). Successful or not, the attempt costs 1 FP.

Entering four-dimensional space – or maneuvering there – requires a roll against Body Sense (GURPS Powers: The Weird, p. 5). You don’t gain the ability to breathe (see Hyperspace, GURPS Powers: The Weird, p. 15), and must hold your breath (GURPS Basic Set, p. 351-352). You can take oxygen with you, but the weight will make Projection harder to achieve."
/>
<element
	name="Remote Hypnosis"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Hypnotism-5."
	prereq="Charisma 1 and Hypnotism; cannot exceed Hypnotism skill."
	desc="In settings where hypnotism is a quasi-mystical process (Psychical Research, GURPS Powers: The Weird, p. 13), a hypnotist may be able to induce a hypnotic trance in a previous subject at a distance. Base time required is five minutes. If Remote Hypnosis succeeds, the subject is in a trance. This may be a trigger for previously implanted suggestions (possibly including “Telephone for instructions”), or a second Remote Hypnosis roll might implant new suggestions, with precision limited as for the Suggest skill (GURPS Basic Set, p. 191).

Modifiers: Hypnotism modifiers (GURPS Basic Set, p. 201); bonus equal to hypnotist’s Charisma; standard range penalties (GURPS Basic Set, p. 550); and modifiers for haste or extra time (GURPS Basic Set, p. 346). If hypnotist and subject have a Special Rapport (GURPS Basic Set, p. 88), the roll is at +5 and base time is only five seconds."
/>
<element
	name="Batching"
	difficulty="Hard"
	default="Any elixir technique."
	prereq="None."
	desc="When making an elixir, an alchemist may accept a -1 penalty to his skill to brew another elixir of the same type, making a “batch” of that elixir. With this technique, you may buy off this penalty for making larger amounts of a given elixir. You must specialize by elixir type and form, which defaults to the base elixir technique; for example, Batching (Endurance/Potion) would be valid but Batching (Endurance) would not. While this technique has no actual limit, you would use the lower of this technique or the unmodified elixir technique when making elixir batches (you can’t get a bonus for making fewer potions)."
/>
<element
		name="Identify Magical Item"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Alchemy-2. Cannot exceed Alchemy+2."
		prereq="None."
		desc="When identifying a possible magical item through Alchemy rather than magic (GURPS Magic, p. 212), use this technique instead."
	/>
<element
		name="Identify Elixir"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Alchemy. Cannot exceed Alchemy+4."
		prereq="None."
		desc="When identifying an elixir (GURPS Magic, p. 212), use this technique instead of your Alchemy."
	/>
<element
		name="Control (Body Part)"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="DX, Judo, Sumo Wrestling, Wrestling; cannot exceed default."
		prereq="None."
		desc="This basic technique allows you to control specific body parts. For example, Control Arm can force your opponent to pull a lever and, defensively, stop his punch, Parry, or aim. Control Hand can make him drop a remote or stop him from pulling a trigger. Control Torso can stop his Dodge. Control techniques cannot force someone to make unarmed/melee attacks or active defenses.

• Control Torso is at -4 for a hand or foot grapple; -3 for two extremities (hands or feet); -2 for a neck, head, arm, or leg grapple; or -1 for two limbs or for one limb and either the neck or head.
• Controlling a limb is at -2 for grappling the torso or the limb’s extremity.
• Control Head works at -2 for a neck grapple, and Control Neck works at -2 for a head grapple.

You can use control techniques to defend against strikes, grabs, or grappling techniques performed with the controlled body part. For defending against grappling techniques, this might only be advantageous if you have a specific setup (see Setup on Pyramid 3/34: Alternate GURPS, p. 17) or are using extra limbs."
	/>
<element
		name="Control Position"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="DX-3, Judo-3, Sumo Wrestling-3, Wrestling-3; cannot exceed default+2."
		prereq="None."
		desc="This technique uses the same location penalties as Control Torso (above). Your opponent may substitute HP for ST in the Grappling Contest when resisting. Use Control Position to rotate your opponent to change his facing, orientation, or posture. If you are rolling and changing posture with him, without changing your relative facing/orientation/posture, you gain +1 and may substitute HP for ST.

Add -2 to change his relative facing between front and rear or between opposite sides. Add -2 to move him from a ground posture to standing. Defensively, use Control Position to stop your foe from changing facing, posture, or orientation. Rotating your foe around is harder when he grapples you; see Taking the Back (above).

Control Position still uses penalties for posture (GURPS Basic Set, p. 231 and GURPS Martial Arts, p. 73), which can be offset by the Low Fighting and Ground Fighting techniques."
	/>
<element
		name="Control Step"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="DX, Judo, Sumo Wrestling, Wrestling-2; cannot exceed default+2."
		prereq="None."
		desc="This technique uses the same location penalties as Control Torso (above). Both you and your opponent may substitute HP for ST in the Grappling Contest. With Control Step, you can move a standing opponent around, by forcing him to step and/or turn with you, or by changing his facing relative to you. Do both at the same time with -1. Changing his relative facing between front and rear or between opposite sides requires an additional -2.

Defensively, use Control Step to stop your opponent from stepping or turning. If your foe is crouching, take -2 to Control Step. Spinning your foe around is harder when he grapples you; see Taking the Back (Pyramid 3/34: Alternate GURPS, p. 14).

This technique is necessary to take a step while grappling, as you need to force your opponent to move. If you are only moving, without turning yourself or your opponent, you may ignore the number of hands/limbs you are grappling with and instead use a flat +1, by pushing or pulling with your full body."
	/>
<element
		name="Pin (Body Part)"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="DX+2, Judo, Sumo Wrestling, Wrestling+2; cannot exceed default."
		prereq="None."
		desc="A pin is a special case of control. If you are pressing your opponent against the ground, by being positioned on top, use Pin (Body Part) instead of Control (Body Part) to defensively stop that part from moving. If you are pressing him against a vertical immobile surface, like a wall, take -1 (which is still a net bonus over Control).

Pin (Body Part) uses the same penalties as Control (Body Part) for affecting adjacent body parts; thus, an attempt to Pin Torso would be at -2 if the closest body part you have grappled is the arm, whether you are directly pressing the torso or the arm. You may substitute HP for ST when pinning."
	/>
<element
		name="Takedown"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-1, Judo-1, Sumo Wrestling-1, Wrestling-3; cannot exceed default."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Takedown uses the same location penalties as Control Torso or Control Leg (see Pyramid 3/34: Alternate GURPS, p. 14); gain +1 if you have both legs grappled or your foe is standing on one leg. Each extra free leg (past the default two) that you have not grappled gives -1.

Specify the direction in which your target will topple; he must land prone, face up, or on his side, with his lower body in his starting hex. If you elect to let go at the end of the technique, he chooses his final posture; otherwise, you decide.

You have three mutually exclusive options for “sacrificing’’ your own posture:
• For +3, fall alongside him, dropping to your choice of prone, face-up, or on your side. You may not change your relative facing. You may substitute HP for ST.
• For +2, pull him down with you, dropping to a kneeling or sitting posture. You may substitute HP for ST.
• For +1, “reap’’ his leg using one of your own; he must have at least one free leg, and you must have at least two.

Immediately after the Takedown, whether you succeed or fail, make a DX roll to not fall over."
	/>
<element
		name="Judo Throw (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-2, Judo-2, Sumo Wrestling-2, Wrestling-4; cannot exceed default."
		prereq="None."
		desc="This technique involves upending or lifting your opponent. It uses Control Torso’s location penalties (see Pyramid 3/34: Alternate GURPS, p. 14), and may be used with Takedown’s sacrificial options (above). You must be standing.

Choose which hexes your opponent lands in when you start to throw; they must overlap or be adjacent to his starting hex. Your foe takes damage as a fall from half of your height (see Falling, GURPS Basic Set, p. 431). You may “drive’’ him to the ground with -1, substituting your thrust damage (+1 for a hard ground surface).

How he lands, and where he takes damage, has five options:
• Land him on his back, lying face-up. This is the default, and damage is to his torso.
• Land him prone (face-down) with -1. Damage is to his torso.
• Land him on his side with -1. Damage is to that side’s arm.
• Land him on his head with -2, after which he falls face-up or on his side. Roll 1d: on a result of 1-3, damage is to his neck; 4-6 indicates skull damage.
• Land him on his head with -3, after which he falls prone. Roll 1d: on a result of 1-3, damage is to his neck; 4-5 damages his skull; 6 damages his face."
	/>
<element
		name="Breakfall (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Acrobatics, Judo, Sumo Wrestling, Wrestling."
		prereq="Acrobatics, Judo, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+4."
		desc="This technique lets you control a fall and reduce damage from being thrown. Roll against Breakfall to reduce the effective height of a fall – including from a Judo Throw – by five yards. If the thrower “drove’’ you to the ground for thrust-based damage, a successful Breakfall reduces damage by 1 plus your margin of success.

If you are landing on your head, Breakfall is at -1. You can change your final landing posture from side to face-up or prone, or vice versa, for -1. You can change it from face-up to prone, prone to face-up, or one side to the other for -2.

If your thrower chose to let go of you, you may roll to a crouch, in the farthest landing hex, for -3. Otherwise, you can flip over into a crouch, still grappled, for -5."
	/>
<element
		name="Wrench Arm (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="DX-3, Judo-3, Sumo Wrestling-5, Wrestling-3; cannot exceed default+3."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the arm; it requires an arm grapple, or takes -2 for a hand grapple."
	/>
<element
		name="Wrench Wrist/Finger (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-4, Judo-4, Sumo Wrestling-6, Wrestling-4; cannot exceed default+4."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the hand. It requires a hand grapple."
	/>
<element
		name="Wrench Leg (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-4, Judo-4, Sumo Wrestling-6, Wrestling-4; cannot exceed default+4."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the leg. It requires a leg grapple, or takes -2 for a foot grapple."
	/>
<element
		name="Wrench Ankle (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-4, Judo-4, Sumo Wrestling-6, Wrestling-4; cannot exceed default+4."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the foot. It requires a foot grapple."
	/>
<element
		name="Wrench Neck (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-3, Judo-3, Sumo Wrestling-5, Wrestling-3; cannot exceed default+3."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the neck. It requires a neck or head grapple."
	/>
<element
		name="Wrench Spine (Alternate)"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-5, Judo-5, Sumo Wrestling-7, Wrestling-5; cannot exceed default+3."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the spine. It requires a torso grapple, done with at least two body parts."
	/>
<element
		name="Bear Hug"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="DX-4, Judo-4, Sumo Wrestling-6, Wrestling-4; cannot exceed default+1."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the torso; it requires a torso grapple. With -2, the victim instead takes fatigue damage as you squeeze out their breath."
	/>
<element
		name="Choke"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-2, Judo-2, Sumo Wrestling-4, Wrestling-2; cannot exceed default+2."
		prereq="None."
		desc="This requires a neck grapple and damages the neck. It can cut off air: if at least 1 point of damage gets past DR, the victim loses 1 fatigue and begins to suffocate. With -2, you may perform a carotid choke instead, which inflicts fatigue damage."
	/>
<element
		name="Head Crush"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="DX-4, Judo-4, Sumo Wrestling-6, Wrestling-4; cannot exceed default+1."
		prereq="None."
		desc="Damage is to the skull, which still has DR 2; it requires a head grapple. With -1, you instead inflict pain as per the Wrench techniques (Pyramid 3/34: Alternate GURPS, p. 16)."
	/>
<element
		name="Beheading Blow"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-5."
		prereq="Any Melee Weapon skill capable of swung cutting attacks; cannot exceed prerequisite skill-2."
		desc="This technique lets slayers buy off the -5 to hit the neck when swinging an edged weapon. It’s valuable against vampires, liches, and other foes susceptible primarily (or only) to beheading."
	/>
<element
		name="Neck Bite"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Brawling-5."
		prereq="Sharp Teeth or Fangs and Brawling; cannot exceed Brawling-2."
		desc="This is a common technique for vampires who find themselves in repeated combat or consider themselves to be great hunters. Werewolves use it just for fun (and some like to follow it up with Neck Snap, GURPS Basic Set, p. 232)."
	/>
<element
		name="Stake to the Heart"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-5."
		prereq="Any Melee Weapon skill capable of thrusting impaling attacks; cannot exceed prerequisite skill-2."
		desc="This technique is most often used with wooden stakes of varying lengths, including improvised stakes such as chair legs and pool cues. It lets slayers buy off the penalty to thrust for the heart with an impaling weapon. It defaults at -5, and not at -3 as for a shot to the vitals, because the target zone is smaller – hitting the lungs, kidneys, etc., has no effect on the undead!"
	/>
<element
		name="Strangle Hold"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Prerequisite skill-3."
		prereq="Judo, Sumo Wrestling, or Wrestling; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="Mummies, disembodied hands (spectral and corporeal), and even a few rippers enjoy this technique. It lets would-be throttlers buy off the penalty to grapple the neck in order to set up a strangle (GURPS Basic Set, p. 370)."
	/>
<element
		name="True Tarot"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="IQ-8."
		prereq="Precognition and Fortune-Telling (Tarot); cannot exceed Fortune-Telling (Tarot)."
		desc="Many precogs subconsciously rely on fortune-telling impedimenta (e.g., crystal balls, yarrow sticks, or tarot cards) or methods (such as palm-reading or augury) to focus their gift. By dint of long training and psychic tuning to such “crutches,” the diviner can increase his odds with deliberate attempts to use Precognition (GURPS Basic Set, p. 77).

Other Fortune-Telling specialties have their own versions of this technique: True Augury, True I Ching, True Scrying, etc."
	/>
<element
		name="Blood Vessel Pressure"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="First Aid-3."
		prereq="First Aid; cannot exceed First Aid skill."
		desc="This technique is a substitute for using a tourniquet (GURPS Low-Tech, p. 145). It can stop bleeding from the scalp, ear, or other location that can’t be tourniqueted but that has accessible blood vessels. The patient must be cooperative or restrained. The caregiver presses against an artery, reducing blood flow and slowing bleeding as for a successful First Aid roll. He may opt to make a ST-based (rather than IQ-based) roll. He must maintain the hold for a full minute, at the cost of 1 FP.

If using Bleeding (GURPS Basic Set, p. 420) and the initial Blood Vessel Pressure roll fails, the medic can maintain the hold at a cost of 1 FP per additional minute. Each minute allows another Blood Vessel Pressure roll, as well as the patient’s HT roll. If either succeeds, the wound doesn’t bleed in that minute.

At the GM’s discretion, this technique can also be based on Pressure Points skill. The prerequisite becomes Pressure Points; the default, Pressure Points-2; and the maximum level, Pressure Points+2."
	/>
<element
		name="Distillation"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Alchemy or Chemistry."
		prereq="Alchemy or Chemistry; cannot exceed prerequisite skill+6."
		desc="Distillation is one of the basic methods for purifying chemical substances. It appears at late TL2, when Roman and Chinese experimenters begin to develop alchemy and chemistry (the two aren’t clearly distinguished until TL5). It’s used to produce alcohol (GURPS Low-Tech, p. 25), among other things.

Roll against Chemistry skill for distillation. The proper temperature is vital and must be judged by observation; a distiller can improve his judgment up to Chemistry+6 using this technique. In a TL5+ lab or distillery, with accurate thermometers, getting the right temperature is easy and the full +6 is automatic. Early thermometers, before Fahrenheit’s (see Temperature and Pressure, GURPS Low-Tech, p. 45), are less accurate, giving only +4. Thermometer bonuses replace technique bonuses; the two never add.

Success doubles the concentration of the desired substance; critical success means the yield is nearly pure. Failure doesn’t change the concentration. Critical failure produces the wrong substance, or (at the GM’s discretion) causes a lab accident such as a burst vessel or a fire."
	/>
<element
		name="Hands-Free Driving"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Teamster (Equines)-4."
		prereq="Teamster (Equines); cannot exceed Teamster (Equines)-1."
		desc="Chariot warriors don’t normally drive their own chariots – their hands are occupied with weapons. They leave the task to a charioteer. If the driver is disabled or unavailable, though, a warrior may loop the reins about his waist or fasten them to his belt, steering by leaning against them. This is never as good as having the reins in hand, and it’s risky; if the chariot is disabled, he’ll be dragged over the ground! He also can’t dodge without losing control of the horses; treat this as a control roll failed by SR or less (see Control Rolls, GURPS Basic Set, p. 466)."
	/>
<element
		name="Mounted Reload"
		difficulty="Hard"
		default="Lower prerequisite skill-3."
		prereq="Guns and Riding; cannot exceed lower prerequisite skill."
		desc="Mounted Reload lets you load a muzzleloader while mounted; see Loading (GURPS Low-Tech, p. 94-95). You must specialize by Guns specialty and Riding specialty. Failure means starting over; critical failure means a dropped weapon, spilled powder or shot, or an extinguished match (matchlock or cannonlock only).

This feat is two-handed. Use Hands-Free Riding (above) for riding more complex than straight-line travel. Any failure means you must start over, in addition to its other bad effects."
	/>
<element
		name="Quick Mount"
		difficulty="Average"
		default="Acrobatics-3, Jumping-3, or Riding-3."
		prereq="Acrobatics, Jumping, or Riding; cannot exceed prerequisite skill."
		desc="For riders before the invention of the stirrup, getting onto a horse was a challenge. It required either stepping onto a mounting block or vaulting onto the horse’s back using this technique. See Mounting Up (GURPS Basic Set, p. 396)."
	/>
</root>